<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Papers delivered in by the commissioners of the kingdom of Scotland at London, to the honorable Houses of the Parliament of England containing, 1. Their answer upon the whole propositions of peace, 2. Reasons touching the militia, 3. The citations of severall passages out of the declaration of the honourable Houses concerning the militia, and uniformity in religion, 4. Reasons why the result of the Committee of Both Kingdoms at Edinburgh, 28 Novem. 1643 is a treaty.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05255</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612240</idno>
  <idno type="VID">179544</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240896915</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1300B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183997</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">52612240</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2793:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Papers delivered in by the commissioners of the kingdom of Scotland at London, to the honorable Houses of the Parliament of England containing, 1. Their answer upon the whole propositions of peace, 2. Reasons touching the militia, 3. The citations of severall passages out of the declaration of the honourable Houses concerning the militia, and uniformity in religion, 4. Reasons why the result of the Committee of Both Kingdoms at Edinburgh, 28 Novem. 1643 is a treaty.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44, 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by order of the Committee of Estates by Evan Tyler his Majesites printer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpieces; initial letters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
                  <note>The first paper delivered in to the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland, containing their answer to the whole propositions of peace -- The second paper, delivered in to the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland, containing reasons touching the militia -- The third paper, delivered in to the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland, concerning the citations of severall declarations of the Houses, concerning the militia, and uniformity of religion -- The fourth paper delivered in to the Houses of Parliament by the Commissioners of Scotland, containing their reasons, why the result of the Committee of Both Kingdomes at Edinburgh 28. Novemb. 1643 is a treaty.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:2"/>
            <p>PAPERS, DELIVERED IN BY THE COMMISSIONERS <hi>OF THE KINGDOME OF</hi> SCOTLAND AT LONDON, To the Honourable Houses of the PARLIAMENT OF ENGLAND: <hi>Containing</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Their Answer upon the whole Propositions of Peace.</item>
                  <item>2. Containing Reasons touching the <hi>Militia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Containing the Citations of several passages out of the Declarations of the said Honourable Houses concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie in Religion.</item>
                  <item>4. Containing Reasons why the Result of the Committee of both Kingdoms at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 28 <hi>November</hi> 1643 is a Treatie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at EDINBURGH <hi>By Order of the</hi> COMMITTEE <hi>of</hi> ESTATES by <hi>Evan Tyler</hi> His Majesties Printer. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="paper">
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179544:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PAPER Delivered in to the Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Commissioners of SCOTLAND: <hi>Containing their Answer to the whole Propositions of Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving considered the Answer of the Honourable Houses assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, of the tenth of April, to our last Paper of the sixth of April: and having to our former paper of the sixteenth of March (expressing our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to a great part of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of Peace, agreed upon by both Houses, together with our dissent in some Particulars, with the reasons thereof, unto which we desired satisfaction) received no other Answer, but that the Houses thought fit to adhere to their former resolutions; And againe to desire our concurrence for the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them to the King. Wee have resolved by this our Reply, to give all possible satisfaction to the Honourable Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the happy ending of this unnaturall and unhappy war, and that we may leave this Kingdome in Peace, and our Armies, Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and our Selves may return in Peace and with Comfort to our Homes and Habitations.</p>
            <p>Wee doe both of us professe an earnest desire of Peace, and for care of the speedy sending of Propositions to the King: And wee do beleeve, that the Parliament may be sufficiently perswaded of the sinceritie of our Desires, if they may be pleased, either to remember for how long a time, how frequently, and how instantly wee have pressed this Point, and have not yet received all the Propositions which they desire to bee sent; Or to consider the sufferings of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179544:4"/>Kingdome of Scotland abroad and at home, since they first gave their assistance to this Kingdome, from which they long to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an honourable and happy Peace; and might have beene long since delivered, if it could have agreed with their Covenant, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Declarations for the good of their Brethren: Or to call to minde how much wee have urged, that the former Propositions of <hi>Uxbridge</hi> agreed upon by both Kingdomes, might be sent to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie, from our just apprehension of the difficulties which might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise from the new Propositions; And which we have represented in conference to a Committee of both Houses, with the reasons of our different judgements in some particulars, conceived by us to be very materiall, and important for the good of both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Wee have no delight to busie our selves, or to be medlers in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters impertinent for us, there be some things which properly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Kingdome of England, their Rights, Lawes and Liberties, which wee desire no more to meddle with, then with the Rights, Lawes, and Liberties of other Kingdomes, and according to our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, will not only consent unto, but endeavour the preservation of them, as England by the like Obligation is bound to consent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and preserve ours. But there be other matters, which either in their owne nature, as being common to both, or by Covenant or Treaty concerne both Kingdomes, wherein unlesse we would forget our Duty to God, to the Kings Majestie, to our own native Kingdom, and to our Brethren, Our common concernment and interest cannot be denied: Were this difference and diversitie rightly apprehended, it might free both the Parliament and us from the obloquies and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of such undiscerning spirits, as notwithstanding our Covenant Treaties, and Ingagements, have no other thoughts of the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the two Kingdomes, then they had before they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Union and Conjunction.</p>
            <p>Wee did not intend by our Paper of the sixth of April, that the resolutions of the Houses should be subjected to the Debates and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of a Committee to be joyned with us: Nor were we so far mistaken, as to conceive that both Kingdomes are bound to a joint advice and judgement, in the preparing and moulding of each one of the Propositions: But because no Cessation, Pacification, or Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whatsoever for Peace, is to be made by either Kingdome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the mutuall advice and consent of both, we conceive that one Kingdome may not send Propositions to the King, or finally deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon Propositions to bee sent for Peace, without the advice as well as consent of the other: For we beleeve the Cessation, Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Agreement mentioned in the Treaty, doth not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in the last Formality, or Solemnity of Peace-making, but also, and chiefly in the materiall Propositions and Foundation, upon which the Peace is finally to be concluded; which once being proposed, and agreed unto by his Majestie, there can be no more question of Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Agreement, but <hi>ipso facto,</hi> a Peace doth necessarily ensue: For as hath beene clearly acknowledged in our late Letters to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179544:4"/>King, the granting of the Propositions to bee sent is the effectuall meanes to give satisfaction and security, especially if desired, and granted by way of Bill, which was unto us the finall security in the year 1641. Also the Peace is to be settled betweene the Kingdomes, as well as betweene them and his Majestie: And in our letter of the the 13. of January to the King wee have both declared, That Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions from both Kingdomes were to bee sent to His Majestie, and that this was the only way for attaining a happy and well grounded Peace. To this joynt Advice and Consent in the Propositions to be sent, wee conceive both Kingdomes are bound by Covenant, which runneth all along upon their joynt Endeavours, for Union against all dividing and separating wayes; especially for Union and Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the matter of Religion, as the chiefest, both Ground and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of their other Conjunction. This joynt Advice and Consent hath beene the constant and continuall Practice of both Kingdoms, in all their Treaties, Demands, Answers, and Resolutions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace, ever since their mutuall Engagement; and particularly in framing and sending the former Propositions, as the joynt desires of both Kingdomes, united by Covenant for the common safety of both. Against this just course, His Majesties Commissioners in the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> endeavoured to divide the desires of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which was then apprehended, resisted, and rejected by the Commissioners of Parliament, and by the Houses themselves, as a dangerous and destructive motion: Nor would the Parliament of England have beene satisfied with the proceedings of the Kingdome of Scotland, their Army, or Commissioners, if they had sent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of Peace to the King for themselves: Only alleadging for themselves, that although they had sent Propositions of Peace to His Majestie, to obtaine His grant thereof, yet they never intended to conclude the Peace without Consent of their Brethren. In this therefore we refer our selves to the common Rule and Principle of Equity received amongst all men.</p>
            <p>Wee might heer have observed the difference betweene Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Agreement whatsoever, betwixt Advice and Consent, and what these doe import, in the 3. and 9. Articles of the same Treaty; and might have added many other reasons, upon which wee will not now insist, but doe earnestly desire and expect, that the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houses in their Wisdome, and from their Love of Peace, will finde out wayes for removing (in a Brotherly manner) the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Judgement about the Propositions to be sent, That our reason being satisfied, we may all agree as well in the means as in the end.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Preface, Title, and Conclusion of the Propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, The matter of Fact doth not answere our desires, which are in Reference to Propositions to be sent from both Kingdomes, and not in reference to any Act depending in the Houses of Parliament, the nature whereof is such as cannot provide for the security of both Kingdomes, as was more fully expressed in our Paper of the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of August 1645: In answere whereunto the Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179544:5"/>in their votes of the eighteenth of that Moneth, did resolve to send Propositions and Bils to His Majestie, wee doe therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the Houses may agree to the sending of the Preface, Title, and Conclusion of the former Propositions, or at least, that they may be to that sense.</p>
            <p>As to the four lines in the front of the Propositions delivered unto us, It is true that the distance of the writing of them to the first Proposition, made us to conceive them to bee no part of that Proposition, but a Preface to the whole; nor could the matter of these lines lead us to another interpretation thereof: But since they are intended by the Houses as an introduction to the first Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee doe agree that there bee an introduction; only wee desire it may bee considered, that the words as they now stand, doe hold foorth, That both Kingdomes were necessitated to undertake this war for their own defence; whereas the Kingdome of Scotland did ingage with their Brethren of England, and undertake this war for the ends expressed in the Covenant, before which the invasion of Scotland was only looked upon as a probable consequent, if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Party had prevailed in England: we do therefore offer these, or the like expressions, for an introduction to the first Proposition.</p>
            <p>Whereas both Kingdomes now united by solemne League and Covenant, have beene necessitated to undertake, and prosecute a just and lawfull war: Or whereas both Houses of Parliament have beene necessitated to undertake a war in their just and lawfull Defence, and afterwards both Kingdomes united by solemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, were engaged for the ends therein expressed to prosecute the same.</p>
            <p>The Introduction to the first Proposition being thus altered, and these words <hi>[Parliament of that Kingdome]</hi> added to these words <hi>[The Convention of Estates]</hi> as is already consented unto by the Houses. Wee doe agree to the first, second, third, and fourth Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions. Concerning the fifth and sixth Propositions; As the matter of Religion, by reason of the necessity and incomparable Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie thereof, deserveth the first place, and before all other matters to bee considered; So hath it beene alwayes in all our undertakings the prime and chiefest of our intentions and desires, and in all our actions and sufferings our greatest Comfort and Encouragement; and which being established according to the Covenant, we are very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident to give and receive satisfaction in all other matters, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Church and Kingdome of Scotland, having beene from the corruption of this fountain overwhelmed with a deluge of miseries, although they had all things beside, cannot bee satisfied, nor think themselves secured: And we confesse, that it is to us, and to that Church and Kingdome no small matter of sorrow, that after so solemn a Covenant, and so many Protestations and Declarations, the Reformation of Religion should so long stick, and bee so much obstructed in this Kingdome, which wee hoped in the beginning, when both Kingdomes entred in Covenant, should long before this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179544:5"/>time have beene not only established here, but propagated also to other Nations, groaning under, or in danger of the yoke of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Tyranny; and which upon the appearing of the light, and the new dawnings of the day in this Island, were beginning to lift up their heads, in expectation of their deliverance and comfort.</p>
            <p>Wee doe therefore desire particularly and explicitely, to know the Articles of Reformation, and Uniformity of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contained under the generall Propositions; all of them after much debate, being long since offered by the Assembly of Divines unto, and a great part of them resolved upon by, both Houses, which may also within a short time resolve upon the remnant. By this meane wee shall proceed the more distinctly and assuredly, and these Articles formed up in a modell, may be considered and granted by the King with the cleerer knowledge, which is very necessary, not only in other Propositions, which are framed as particularly as may be, but also and especially in the matter of Religion.</p>
            <p>This was the Course approved and observed at the Treaty at <hi>Ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> where so much as was at that time prepared for settling Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was presented. If wee should without the knowledge of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars rest upon the generall Proposition, Peace might bee settled without the setting of Religion, except in so far as by the Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, the Power of Reformation is to be in the Houses, and Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Religion is placed in the Parliaments of both Kingdomes, which doth not answere our Covenant, binding both Kingdomes to the exercise of their Power, by their Endeavours, in the particulars therein specified. Nor will this generall give satisfaction to any of the Reformed Churches, especially to the Church of Scotland: Nor will it be able to cure the present Distempers of Religion in the Church of England, which call for a present Reformation, nor se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them or us from altering of that which is already ordained, nor be any recompence of the many labours and sufferings, and the much expence of Treasure and bloud in this Cause.</p>
            <p>Having perused the severall Ordinances, Directions, and Votes of the Honourable Houses concerning Church-government delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us, which wee conceive will be the matter of the Propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion, and in this sense only wee speak to them. Wee doe agree to the direction for the present election of Elders, to the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of Congregationall, Classicall, Provinciall, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Assemblies, and to the Direction concerning the members of which they are constitute, and the times of their meeting: Only wee desire, That no godly Minister bee excluded from being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Classicall Presbytery, nor any godly Minister having law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Commission, from being a member of the Provinciall and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Assemblies, and there being the greater need of their presence and assistance in such Assemblies, that there be no Ruling Elders to joyne with, and assist them. And wee desire that a fixed time bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the ordinary meeting of the Nationall Assembly, with Power to the Parliament to summon them when they please, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179544:6"/>with Liberty to the Church to meet oftner, if there shall be necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cause; the ordinary meeting thereof being most necessary for preserving Truth and Unity in the whole Church. Against the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that may arise and multiply in the Church, and against the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions and Differences that may distract the inferiour Assemblies of the Church, and for receiving and determining Appeales from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Assemblies, which otherwise will be infinite, and lye over without determination, and the exigence of Religion sometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such, that it will require an extraordinary meeting; Wee agree to the Rules and Direction concerning Supsension from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper, in cases of Ignorance and Scandall: On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we desire that the Congregationall Elderships may have power to judge in cases of scandall not enumerated, with liberty to the Person grieved to appeale as in other Reformed Churches. This wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to bee a Power no more arbitrary in this Church then in them who are limited by the rules expressed in Scripture, and do exercise this their power with such moderation, as is a Comfort, Help, and Strengthning of Civil Authority. The appointing of Provinciall Commissioners, such as are appointed in the Ordinance, will minister Occasion to such Debates and Disputes in this and other Churches, as will bee very unpleasant to Parliaments and Civil Powers, will make a great disconformity betwixt this and other Churches, and a present Rent and Division in this Church is such a mixture in Church Government, as hath not beene heard of in any Church before this time, may prove a foundation of a new Episcopacy, or of a High-Commission; and the Work may be better done by the Assemblies of Ministers and Ruling Elders, who have this in their Ecclesiasticall Charge, and will be no lesse tender of the Honour of the Parliament, by whose Lawes they live and are protected, and as able and willing to give just satisfaction to the People, whose Consciences and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation are best known unto them, as any other persons whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Concerning the Supsension of the Ministers themselves, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though scandall in them deserveth double censure, yet wee conceive it to bee most agreeable, that they have their Censure from the Clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicall, or other Superior Assemblies of the Church, where there bee Ministers to judge them. Wee do also agree to the Ordinance of Ordination of Ministers, only wee desire it may bee provided that it stand in force for all time to come: And therefore it may bee consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, whether the two last Paragraphes of the Ordinance doe not belong to the Ordination, which was extraordinary, and <hi>pro Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There bee other matters contained in the Ordinances, of which some are touched by the Commissioners of the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in their late Remonstrance, March 26. given in to the Houses, such as the manner of Subordination of the Assemblies of the Church to the Parliament, so much subject to mistake the seeming exemption of some sorts of persons from the just censures of the Church, the ministring the Sacrament to some persons, against the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179544:6"/>Conscience of the Ministrie and Eldership: Concerning publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to be only before the Elderships and such like, which may bee taken into consideration, and with small labour and alteration bee determined, to the great satisfaction of many. As for the remnant, concerning the perpetuall Officers of the Church, and their Offices, The Order and Power of Church Assemblies, The Order of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Repentance, and of proceeding to Excommunication and Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, wee desire they may bee agreed upon according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Advice of the Divines of both Kingdoms, long since offered to both Houses: which being done, they may bee presently drawne in a Method, and formed up in a Modell of Church-government in three dayes, to the quieting the mindes of all the Godly, concerning the particular meaning of both Kingdomes in the matter of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the great content of the reformed Churches, and which will both make us distinctly to know what wee demand, and send to the King, and that He may know what He doth grant.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Clause for ratifying the Acts of the Convention of Estates and Parliament of Scotland, alleaged to be set downe in too generall Termes. The chief thing we desire in that Article, is, That the Convention of Estates and Parliament may be ratified, because the Authority of them hath beene questioned by the King. And it may bee remembred, that wee did heartily joyne with the Houses, in denying to treate with His Majestie, untill Hee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged this Parliament. As for the Acts of the Convention and Parliament, the most materiall of them are for levying Men and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for the assistance of this Kingdome, and the Kingdome of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and our own Defence at home against those Rebels that inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us for our engaging in this Cause: of which Acts wee are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deliver in a List to the Houses.</p>
            <p>As concerning future Acts, although that was agreed to in the former Propositions, yet that all Scruples may be removed, wee shall adde this restriction [And to such other Acts for raising of Money, for payment of the publick Debts and Damages of the Kingdome and other publick Uses, and for disposing of Delinquents Estates, as shall bee hereafter agreed on by the Estates of Parliament] Upon which Considerations we are confident the Houses will rest satisfied with the equity of our Desires concerning this Clause, which being added, we do agree to the 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12 Propositions.</p>
            <p>As to the difference about the 13. Proposition, we hope we made it sufficiently appear to the Committee of both Houses, That the transactions at Edinburgh 28 November 1643 are a Treaty: It being evident from the credentiall Letters given to the Commissioners of both Houses, That they had full and ample power to Treat, agree, and conclude, Articles being mutually agreed upon, to satisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a starved Army, and by their stay to preserve a Kingdom from ruine. These Articles being confirmed by the Houses, and the Votes of the Houses delivered, as their consent to that Treaty; And the Kingdom of Scotland desired thereupon to co-operate with them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179544:7"/>for the stay of that Army, great supplies of Moneys and Provisions being advanced upon that Agreement by the Kingdom of Scotland, and thanks returned to them for the same by the Houses: Also assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance given by their Letters, that they had ratified the severall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties between the Kingdoms: In all which, we trust the Houses will receive satisfaction from the Reasons given at the Conference, and other grounds since discovered, which we have thought fit to set down in a Paper annexed: And if any further scruples or doubts shall arise, which have not been answered, we are so far perswaded of the trueth and reality of that Treaty, as we are confident to clear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them upon a friendly debate.</p>
            <p>We have hitherto debated whether that agreement made at Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh 28 November be a Treaty or not; But no considerations have yet been offered what Inconvenience there might be to the affairs of Ireland, by reason of any particular in that agreement, wherein as the Kingdome of Scotland must be carefull of the good and security of their Forces in Ireland, so will they be alwayes tender of what may be for the good of the affairs of the Crown of England; and thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest that they have no other ends before them, but the unanimous and effectuall prosecution of that War, which shall be no sooner ended nor the Army satisfied and dismissed, but they will with all readinesse and cheerfulnesse recall their Forces out of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>As to the first part of the 14. Proposition, we desire it may stand as formerly, for the Reasons afore-mentioned: And as to the last part, we still desire that all the Articles concerning the settling of Religion in this Kingdom may be extended to Ireland, because we are bound by our Covenant to endeavour Reformation in the Church of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms to the neerest Conjunction and Uniformity in Religion; and because the name of Protestant Religion is so generall, as many Sects and Heresies make claim unto it.</p>
            <p>The 15. Proposition we have not yet received.</p>
            <p>The 16. and 17. Propositions are agreed upon.</p>
            <p>As to the 18. Proposition, we desire that the <hi>Militia</hi> may be so firmly settled, as neither the King nor any other be able to disturbe or infringe the Peace now to be agreed upon: And although it be our judgement, that the former Propositions are a more firme Securitie for conserving the Peace, and a stronger Band of Unity betwixt the Kingdoms then the new, and are therefore desirous the Houses would be pleased to send the former; which being granted by his Majestie, we think the <hi>Militia</hi> perfectly secured, and that the War should not be continued by insisting upon the new Propositions: Yet lest our disagreement herein with the Houses, should be a hinderance to the sending of Propositions, That we may testifie how desirous we are, so far as in us lies, to give the Houses satisfaction, And how much we value the speedy settling of the Peace of these Kingdomes above our own interest; Provided that it be understood to be without prejudice to the right and interest of the Crown, which we understand to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179544:7"/>conjoyned with the respective Parliaments in the <hi>Militia</hi> of both Kingdoms, and not to be absolutely in the King himself, And that the King and his posterity be not totally excluded, and rendred incapable to concurre with their Parliaments, for protecting of their Subjects, and opposing the enemies of the Kingdoms; And provided, that it be without prejudice to the severall Treaties between the Kingdoms: We do consent that the power, exercise, and managing of the <hi>Militia</hi> in each Kingdom, be settled in the Parliaments of either Kingdoms respectively, for the space of such a time as shall be mutually agreed upon; And after expiration of that Term, That the <hi>Militia</hi> be settled and exercised, in such manner, and by such wayes and means as shall be agreed upon by his Majestie and the Parliaments of either King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom respectively, whereby the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> of England and Ireland, which by the former Propositions was in Commissioners of both Kingdoms, will be in the Houses of Parliament: The people will be secured from all apprehensions of danger, by reason of the late Troubles; And the King, who is one of the three Estates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will not be for ever excluded from that just power and interest in the <hi>Militia</hi> by which he may concurre with the Parliament in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kingdom. And the Propositions for the <hi>Militia</hi> being thus qualified, we do agree to the 18. Proposition, and the two first branches thereof. To the third branch of the <hi>Militia,</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning the Forces of both Kingdoms, We cannot agree; In regard as it is now conceived, it may import (as we declared at the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) that after the Peace is settled one of the Kingdoms may send Forces into the other, without the advice and consent of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to which they are sent. And further, it is defective, in that there is no provision made therein for joyning the Forces of the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in the Intervals of Parliament. We do therefore desire in stead thereof, in pursuance of the large Treaty, and according to the Votes of both Houses of the 26 of March, concerning the Conservation of the peace to be settled betwixt the Kingdoms, That Commissioners be nominated by both Houses of Parliament, of persons of known integrity, and such as both Kingdoms may confide in, for their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to Religion, and peace of the Kingdoms, who may have the power expressed in the large Treaty for that Peace, and who may meet as a joynt Committee with the Conservers of the peace to be nominated and appointed by the Estates of the Parliament of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and have power to do as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To preserve the Peace betwixt the Kingdoms and the King, and every one of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To prevent the violation of the Articles of Peace, or any troubles arising in the Kingdoms by breach of the said Articles, And to hear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all differences that may occasion the same, according to the Treaties; And to do further, according as they shall respectively receive Instructions from the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland, and the Houses of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England for the time, mutually to be agreed upon, and after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179544:8"/>of that terme, from his Majestie and the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland, and the Houses of the Parliament of England respectively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To conjoyn the Forces of both Kingdoms to resist all Forraign Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and suppresse any Forces raised within any of the Kingdoms, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance of the publike Peace of the Kingdoms or any of them, by any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity under the Great Seale, or other Warrant whatsoever, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland, or their respective Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners in the Intervals of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the full security of these Kingdoms, as well from Forraign Troubles as intestine Insurrections; We desire, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position formerly agreed upon between the Kingdoms, The making and concluding of Peace or War, The making of a Truce or Cessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any Treaties for the same with Forraign Princes and States, May be with the advice and consent of the Parliaments of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Scotland and England, or in the Intervals of Parliament, the Commissioners for Conservation of the peace, and not otherwise. This is ordinary, and universally observed in all mutuall Leagues that are both offensive and defensive, though there be not a Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which is the strictest tye of all others. It is also most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for the Peace of these Kingdoms, because War made or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by any one of the Kingdoms against a Forraign Nation, doth make both Nations by reason of their union under one Head and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, to be lyable to the Inconveniences of the War both by Sea and Land; and therefore it ought to be done by the advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of both: Or the Kingdom making or denouncing War to a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Nation, without the consent of the other, would be oblieged to keep the other free from damage, and refound what losse the other shall sustain thereby. And whereas both Houses have been pleased to alter the wayes and means agreed upon between the Kingdoms in the former 17 Proposition, concerning the communication of their Councells: And whereas their Lordships have offered in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to our Paper of the 6 of April to give their consent, that such Propositions should be presented to the King as we conceived to be for the good and security of the Kingdom of Scotland, In regard of the great advantage which a Kingdom enjoyeth by the Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and ordinary Residence of their Soveraign with them; And the great losse and prejudice which the other Kingdom doth sustaine through their absence, by their not understanding the disposition of their people or condition of their affairs, but from the Informations of others intrusted by the Kingdom; besides many other prejudices, better felt by the Kingdom of Scotland, then can by us be here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</p>
            <p>Wee doe therefore earnestly desire the consent of the Honourable Houses, for sending to His Majestie a Proposition, That the King and the Prince, and after them their Heires and Successors, shall at least one year of three reside in Scotland, where they may personally dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that duety they owe to the Subjects of that Kingdome, where
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179544:8"/>Conscience cannot allow them to bee alwayes non-residents, nor the welfare of the Kingdome dispence with their constant absence.</p>
            <p>Upon the like causes and grounds, Wee desite the Honourable Houses to concurre with us in a desire to His Majestie, That in all places of Trust, and Offices about the King, Queene, and Prince, and rest of his Royall Children, The equall half, or at least the third part, may be of the Scottish Nation, lest by time they become stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, each unto other, which must needs produce inconveniencies: And this we trust will not bee interpreted as the casting in of any Let or Hinderance to retard the Propositions; Sith the Honourable Houses have given us so good Hopes of their Consent, without debate, to such Propositions as we conceive to bee conduceable for the good and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of the Kingdome of Scotland.</p>
            <p>Concerning the 19. Proposition: Seeing by Gods providence both Nations are in one Island, speake One and the same Language, professe One and the same Religion, are united under the same Head and Monarch, and are now more firmely joyned by their late solemne League and Covenant: and it being already agreed upon betweene the Honourable Houses and us in this Proposition, That His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties assent shal be desired to what the two Kingdomes shall agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in prosecution of the Articles of the large Treaty which are not finished. We do earnestly desire the Honourable Houses to agree unto these Articles, so farre as shall bee insisted upon by the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland, which will be a Testimony of the Affection and Brotherly kindnesse of this Kingdome to their Brethren, who did so chearfully and seasonablely come in for their help and assistance.</p>
            <p>The 20 and 21. Propositions are agreed upon.</p>
            <p>As for the four omitted Propositions which concerne the joint in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of both Kingdomes, Wee desire they may bee sent with the other Propositions to His Majestie for His consent, These being of greater concernment to the Kingdomes, then other Propositions which are desired to be sent at this time; Some of them are so necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as a peace cannot be setled without them; As in particular, the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of Armies, without which the Kingdom of Scotland cannot have peace, there being still a body of Rebells by Commission from His Majesty in the Mountaines of Scotland which do infest the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, The Act of oblivion also is the very Bond of Peace.</p>
            <p>Having this exprest our sense upon the whole Propositions, both in our condiscension and consent, and in our discent and difference, which hath not proceeded from our presuming to be Judges of what may properly belong to the good of the Kingdome of England, but we conceive is grounded upon, and warranted by the Covenant, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; Declarations of both Kingdoms, as wil appear by the annexed Papers: We desire that such of the Propositions as the Kingdome of Scotland is concerned in, may be so framed, as that we may give our full consent to the sending of them: Or otherwise, as we did former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer for our selves, We desire to hear from the Houses such over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and expedients, as may determine our differences, and stand with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179544:9"/>our Covenant, Treaties, and Declarations: If this our Desire be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as our Hope is, the Propositions may bee speedily sent; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise it is apparant, the stop is not in us; And we shall wish it may be seriously laid to heart, what a lamentable close it will bee of a suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessefull Warre, wherein both Kingdoms have been deeply engaged by so Sacred and Solemne a Covenant; Either to make no peace, or to make a divided peace without establishing of Religion, which is that which was principally intended, and promiseth the greatest bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing from the God of Trueth and Peace, the Author of our union, and great Master of this his owne work, wherein his Hand hath been manifestly seene untill this day.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="paper">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179544:9"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PAPER, Delivered in to the Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Commissioners of SCOTLAND: <hi>Containing Reasons touching the</hi> MILITIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> wee do with all willingnesse and alacrity agree, that it bee setled, as may bee most for the security of both Kingdomes, that the King, nor no other be ever able to disturbe nor infringe the Peace, nor involve us in a new War: But wee conceive the former Propositions concerning the <hi>Militia</hi> should stand, and bee sent to the King, rather then the new, as they are now altered: And there be two principall Grounds which move us to be of this judgement; One is, That the setling of the <hi>Militia</hi> according to the former Propositions, is a great deal better for the Security, Safety, and Unity of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, for the which wee gave many Reasons in our Debates and Answers to severall Objections, which heer wee need not to repeat, seeing out of our earnest desire of Peace, we are willing to satisfie the Houses in that point. The other is, from what may bee justly obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by His Majestie against it; for which we do offer to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships consideration some few reasons of many that might bee given, hoping no man will take any exception, nor mistake us for what wee propound for the Right and Interest of the Crown, and of the Kingdomes in the Crown upon this Subject: For 1. Wee may without Vanity averre, That as the Kingdome of Scotland did not flatter His Majestie, when Hee was in the height of His Power; so now when the King is at His lowest ebbe, they will make Conscience not to take away what they conceive to bee that just Royall Power and Authority, which both Nations by their Allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179544:10"/>and Covenant acknowledge to bee in the Crown, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Preservation of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdomes, and which they are oblieged therein to maintaine. 2. That our Debates are only from these grounds, and for no other end, and that wee do not speak of extraordinary cases, and extreme dangers of the Kingdome, when ordinary remedies are refused, <hi>Ubi salus Populi Lex suprema,</hi> as in the time and case of this war, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Parliament should provide for the safety of the Kingdome. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe wee speak to deny any present meanes of full security of these Kingdomes, from new and after-blasts of this late Storme, which wee all grant, and are most ready by all lawfull and possible wayes to secure: But we speak of the ordinary and constant Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome and <hi>Militia</hi> thereof, after a settled and solid Peace. 3. That wee neither did, nor intend to debate for the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> to bee in the Crown alone, as the Kings Declarations and Commissioners at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> did contend, and which hath beene one of the causes of all these unhappy Troubles; but that it may bee jointly in the Kings Majestie, and the two Houses of the Parliament, who make up the three Estates of the Kingdome, and who are intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted with the supreme Power and Government thereof, as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Declarations from time to time, and their Commissioners at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> did contest; and from whom jointly no danger or trouble can be feared, or apprehended by, or to the Kingdom, especially seeing we concur to the suspending the execution and exercise of that power in the King, for such a definite time as shall be agreed upon.</p>
            <p>Having thus prefaced and stated the Question, which wee desire to be remembred throughout all the Debate, albeit we do not repeat it in every place, wee conceive for the reasons in our former Paper, and these other after following, That the King, His Posterity, and the Crown, should not for all time coming be divested of all Power, Right, and Interest in the matter of the <hi>Militia,</hi> so as (although they were never so willing to follow the advice of their Parliaments, yet) they shall for ever bee made incapable, and in no time coming bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to joyn with their Parliaments, for resisting their Enemies, and the Enemies of the Kingdome, and protecting their Subjects.</p>
            <p>That by the fundamentall Lawes, and constant Practise of the most legall and best regulated Kingdomes, and by the Lawes and Practise of these Kingdomes declared to the world by the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houses, the power of war and the <hi>Militia,</hi> is placed in the King and Parliaments, and is so acknowledged by all that write upon this Subject for Parliaments, which is directly contrary to this new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, by which the whole power of the <hi>Militia</hi> is solely placed in the Houses of Parliament, and the Crown excluded for ever.</p>
            <p>That in the Petitions, Messages, and Declarations sent to the King, emitted to the Kingdom, and to all the World, we have professed that no more was sought concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> but that it might be intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted to such Persons, as the Parliament should nominate or approve, &amp; might confide in, for their affection and fidelity to Religion and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179544:10"/>Kingdome, without diminution of the Kings Authority or just <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap>ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; And that His Majesties granting Commission to su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, was a sufficient Security for the Safety of His Person, Honour, Crowne, and Authority. And for preventing all jealousies betwixt Him and His People, and preventing all Feares and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Kingdomes, and the mischievous designes of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And for better remembrance, wee shall offer herewith in the annexed Paper, some particulars set down in their former Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, whereof the most part were sent to Scotland to inform them of the quarrell, and ingage them therein, and their intentious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, to preserve and defend the Kings Person and Authority, in the preservation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdomes (That the world may beare witnesse with our Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of our Loyalty, and that wee have no thoughts or intentions to diminish His Majesties just Power and Greatnesse) was used as a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Argument, to perswade Scotland to joyne with England in this Warre; And is a part of the third Article of our Covenant, by which wee are likewise bound in the same Article, mutually to preserve the Rights and Priviledges of the Parliament; and wee doe conceive, that what God, the fundamentall Lawes and Practises of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and our Covenant have conjoined, should not be divided. And now to exclude the King and His Posterity for ever (as may be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently collected from the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge</hi>) will be understood to bee an alteration of the fundamentall Government, contrary to the former Resolutions and Declarations of both Kingdomes, and not agreeable to our Covenant.</p>
            <p>The settling of the <hi>Militia</hi> according to the new Proposition, may disable the Crown from ever performing that duety, which all Kings by their Royall Office, and Oath of Coronation are oblieged to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and their Subjects by their oath of Alleageance bound to assist, for the Protection of their Subjects and the Laws, and opposing their enemies, and keeping friendship and correspondance with their allyes.</p>
            <p>That the two Kingdomes being by Gods providence happily now United, and Conjoyned in the Crowne by loyall Subjection and Alleageance to one Soveraigne and Head, as is expressed in the large Treaty 1641. And this Union by our Protestation, our Oath of Parliament, the fifth Article of the Covenant, being to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and perpetuated to Posterity, we desire not by our consent to loose so strong a link of that Golden chaine betweene the Kingdoms, Especially seeing this in one age or other may bee used by a secluded Crowne, as a meane and a motive to ingage in trouble these Nations now separated in their <hi>Militia,</hi> which we are bound to foresee and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; Yea, even in any one of the Kingdoms, The Kings Posterity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on the power of their Predecessors, may bee soone incited to endeavour by new Stirs to regaine it, whereas the power remaining in them with the advice of their Parliaments, may preserve the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in peace, <hi>quo equiorem eo firmiorem Pacem,</hi> we may expect to us and our Posterity after us.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179544:11"/>
            <p> In our Paper of the 20 of February at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> the power of the war in Ireland is acknowledged to bee in the Crown radically, and the execution of it by a power derived from it, exercised by others: And hath not the Crown the like power concerning war in England as in Ireland? Yea, this is also acknowledged in the Paper of the 22. of February at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> concerning the <hi>Militia</hi> of England and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; and that it is no otherwise to bee exercised then by Authority from His Majestie and both Houses of the Parliament of England, and the Estates of the Parliament of Scotland respectively. Whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will read that Paper, and withall remember the Kings Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, albeit Hee were vanquisht and made Prisoner, to quit His Life and Estate both, before Hee thus uncrowned the Crown, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed His Posterity, as <hi>pag.</hi> 313, 314, 316, 320, 321, 380. and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places He doth professe, may easily judge if this bee the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test way for a speedy and durable Peace, which with Truth is the Sum of all our Desires.</p>
            <p>To our former reasons, The Committee of both Houses did give the subsequent Answers and Arguments, for their adhering to the new Proposition concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> which wee set down accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our best remembrance, but in case of any forgetfulnesse or mistake, shall be most ready to rectifie and satisfie the same.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That the safety and security of England depends upon the setling of the</hi> Militia, <hi>and therefore next to Religion, is that which they have most reason to stick upon, and crave satisfaction in it, that which the Houses upon so mature deliberation have thought fit for themselves, and the security of this Kingdome, ought not to be contradicted by us; and that it seems very hard, that another Kingdome should dignosce that for which this Kingdom hath smarted, and beene at so much expence, and to desire that the Power should be put into that Hand which hath wounded them, and from whom they have sustained so great misery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> To which it was and is replyed, Wee doe acknowledge that a firme Peace is next to Truth to be preferred to all other things: And our most earnest Desire is, that it may bee speedily obtained, but a just and equall Peace is the best and most durable. The former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions were upon long and mature deliberation of both Kingdoms agreed unto; and seeing Scotland hath suffered (according to their measure and proportion) no lesse then England, and hath ingaged for them and with them in the danger, and are subject to the like for the future, wee have the same interest in the remedy, and cannot bee thought to wrong England, when wee are as tender of them as of our selves, for both Nations have beene wounded with the same Hand, and should therefore have the same cure. It is very far from our thoughts to desire that the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> may be in the Kings Hand alone who hath wounded us, but that it may bee in the King and Parliament joyntly, and that the exercise and managing of it bee only by the advice of the Parliaments: And as these hands joyntly did never wound, so they cannot but secure the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and was all that ever of before was craved by themselves for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179544:11"/>their perfect security. Likeas, it seemes to conduce most for the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the Peace betweene the Kingdomes, that the <hi>Militia</hi> of either bee in the King and Parliament joyntly, because then they both must be ingaged before there be any trouble between the Nations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwise the one might do it.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That they have not disputed such tender Points with us, although we have done as much in Scotland, and that they know their own Laws best, and that none should judge of them, or can interpret them but themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Wee acknowledge that the Points which are in Debate are very tender, and do wish that the Differences betweene the King and His Kingdoms had never come to such a height, as to bring so tender points in dispute; and the more tender they are, we desire they may be the more tenderly handled, that wee never knew of any such thing done in Scotland, and that we were most tender of the Kings Power and Authority in the time of our greatest Differences, and are most willing to concurre in all wayes for the security of this Kingdome, which we crave for the security of Scotland: That we know and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Independency of the Kingdomes, except upon God and their Soveraigne, as is more fully exprest in the entry of the large Treaty, and that wee doe not take upon us to judge of, or interpret their Laws, but may without any offence or presumption remember them of what they have declared to us, to be according to their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes, and originall Constitution of the Government of this Kingdom, and wherein the interest of both Kingdoms for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the King (upon the grounds of our Covenant, and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the King and Kingdome, and to all the World) is common, we ought to be satisfied in our Judgements and Consciences, in what wee are to consent unto, especially that nothing be contrary unto our common Ingagements and Declarations.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That their Declarations were framed, published, and made use of, as their affairs stood then: But after so much bloud-shed by the King, and so much expence of this Kingdome, they may alter these Declarations now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Their former Declarations being made during the same war, cannot bee so easily altered, in respect of the Subjectand Nature of them, many of them being promis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap>ory and declaratory to all the World, and not without deep attestations of the Name of God, and some of them particulary to the Kingdome of Scotland, that they would never seek nor take that or the like power from the Crown, and that no trouble or successe should ever change their resolutions, which was a chief motive and argument of Scotlands ingaging with them in the war.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That in the new Proposition for the</hi> Militia <hi>there is Freedome and Power to joine such forces of both Kingdomes, as either Kingdome shall think fit, which doth secure both against forrain invasion or intestine war, and if there bee any inconvenience in the form, as it is conceived in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, it may be remedied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> That clause of sending such Forces as the Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall think fit to joyne with the Forces of Scotland, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179544:12"/>in the Proposition, is a prejudice rather then advantage to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdom, importing a power to send Forces unto the other, without their own desire or consent: And the mending of the form of it will not be so good a security, either to keep the Kingdoms joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or prevent War, as the former Propositions was.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That the King will have interest and power with Commissioners, and may tempt them more easily then Hee can do the Houses of Parliament, Commissioners cannot be so limited, but they will be easily tempted, if Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy be kept at such a height, as we propose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Though the King may have power with Commissioners, yet there is a remedy provided in the Proposition, that the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners shall be comptable to the Houses, and alterable whensoever they please. And although the power which was formerly in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners were put in the Houses, Yet it should be so done, as not to take away the whole power from the Crown, and the remedy in the Intervals; And may be without dividing the two Kingdoms in the conjunction of their Councels and Forces: And the King and Crown so secluded, will have more power to ingage Kingdoms so divided in a War, then if the former Proposition shall stand. We desire not Monarchy to be at a height of absolute Soveraignty, nor of an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Tyrannicall power; Neither desire we just Monarchicall power to be wronged, and rendred contemptible; But to have such a golden Mediocrity, as they may be able, by the advice of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, to protect their Subjects and oppose their Enemies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as is settled by the fundamentall Laws and ancient Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Kingdom, Declared to all the world by the honourable Houses.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That the putting the power of the</hi> Militia <hi>in the Houses doth not wrong the King more, or disagree from our Covenant, then to have it put in Commissioners; And seeing we did assent that by the former Propositions the</hi> Militia <hi>should be put in Commissioners, Why do we now disassent to have the same put in the Houses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> 1. That Proposition was then conceived with a conjunction of the Kingdoms; This, by separating them, leaves them more open to temptations from a secluded Crown. 2. The right and power of disposing the <hi>Militia,</hi> being controverted between the King and the Houses, the putting of the exercise and managing thereof in Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, who were to have their Commission and power from the King and Parliament, was a clear acknowledgment (as is confessed by your Paper of the 22 of February at <hi>Uxbridge</hi>) and a legall esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment (as it is called by the Parliament in their Declaration <hi>pag.</hi> 710) that the right and power of the <hi>Militia</hi> was in the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament joyntly, and the Commissioners were as a third confident Person intrusted by both; and that course had been at most, but a suspending the exercise and execution of that power for a time neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for our security: But if upon contestation of right, the King shall acknowledge the whole power of the <hi>Militia</hi> to be onely in the two Houses of Parliament, or renounce his right unto them, the Crowne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179544:12"/>will be excluded for ever. And it was professed in the Debate, to be intended to take the right, power, and interest it self from the Crown, untill the Parliament shall be pleased to restore it, upon experience of the carriage of the Crown, which certainly never had any miscariage, whatsoever may be the fault of any Person intrusted therewith for his time, but it is the Original and fundamentall security of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>There was no time limited in the former Propositions, which did limit the endurance of the</hi> Militia, <hi>And therefore there ought to be no limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of time in the new Proposition, since there was none in the former: and the one is no more against the Covenant then the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> The former was sent as a Proposition to be Treated upon by Commissioners on both sides, and the time in the former Proposition was indefinite, and so was not terminate to any time, long or short: And upon debate at the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> (after consultation with the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses) the time was limited to seven yeers: But by the new Proposition (whereunto a positive answer is desired to be craved without any Treaty, yea mention made of incorporating it with the rest in one Bill) the continuance of the <hi>Militia</hi> in the Houses is made perpetuall; and so not onely exclusive of the present exercise, but of the perpetuall right of the Crowne. This distinction between the Right and the Exercise, the Power and the Execution of it, the abolition of the one, and suspension of the other, is set down in your first Remonstrance <hi>pag.</hi> 17. admitted by the King 249. and renewed by your Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners at <hi>Uxbridge, pag.</hi> 120.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That although the time for the continuance of the</hi> Militia <hi>in the Proposition be perpetuall, yet the Parliament can limit the time when they please, and may give the King enlargement of power: That the prefixing a time to the</hi> Militia <hi>will give occasion to prepare plots of trouble against that time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> What they may do, may not be done: But it is our present dutie and obligation, not to take away and diminish his just power and authority. After the expiring of the prefixed time, the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> is not to be ordered, but as the King with consent of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Parliament, shall think fit; nor can he dispose of it any way without consent of the Houses, which we desire may still be so, but would not have the Crowne totally excluded from the <hi>Militia,</hi> and rendred incapable for ever to joyne in the disposing of it with the Houses of Parliament, Especially seeing the perpetuall exclusion of of the Crowne from the <hi>Militia,</hi> is not necessary for, but prejudiciall to, our security, because the residence of the Supreme power (both for making and protecting of Laws) in the Crowne and Parliament, hath ever been the Originall, fundamentall, and the perpetuall security of the Kingdoms: and neither the one nor the other can be taken away totally and finally, without a totall and finall change of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it self.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That for the right and just interest of the Crown, none will be more tender then the English, but that the King hath no right but for the good of the Kingdom, And since they conceive, that it is better to have the</hi> Militia <hi>in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179544:13"/>the Houses, the King can have no right to it. Although the power of the</hi> Militia <hi>had beene in the King, yet when that power is abused, it may and should be suspended, and may be restored when the Parliament shall think fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> The King and Kingdome are <hi>relata,</hi> And as the good of the Kingdome is the good of the King, so is the good of the King, the good of the Kingdome. And because both the Kings Authority, and the priviledges of the Parliament are for the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (which cannot have the Being or Welbeing of a Kingdome without the Crowne, nor a Crowne without the Sword and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) therefore have we Promised, Protested, and Sworne, to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Preserve, and Defend both the one and the other, which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing then to obey mutable Lawes, whereof there is not one word in our Protestations and Covenants for that very same cause of their mutability. And we doe not desire, that the right of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> be onely in the King; But that it may remaine in the King and Parliament, according to the fundamentall Lawes and practise of the Kingdome, And that it bee managed and exercised in such a way as may be best for the security of both. Although the execution and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of the power in any Person, may be suspended for a time when it is abused, and the limitation of it is necessary for the securitie of the Kingdome, yet the right cannot bee totally taken away, and the Crowne deprived of it for ever.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>Judgement of Courts is without the King, and yet the King is not wronged, that although the King be not personally in His Parliament, yet Hee is virtually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Judgement of Courts and their Power is derived from King and Parliament, and there is not so much of Power granted to bee in the King, in the point of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and the judgement of Courts is but of particular cases betweene Person and Person, but the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> is a generall and universall Power, for the safety of King and Kingdome; and therefore the Power of it is both in King and Parliament, to protect as wel as to make Laws. After the enacting of the Proposition, Hee can bee no more esteemed to bee virtually nor actually there, concerning that whereabout Hee is declared to have no vertue nor power, but divested of all right and interest, as heer in the matter of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The King contends that no Law in Scotland is valide without the touch of the Scepter, yet we are not pleading for the Kings right therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> There is no such Law, far lesse a fundamentall Law in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and least of all any Declaration of the Parliament of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for it, upon a contest between the King and them, as all these are in this case now in Debate of the Kings Right of the <hi>Militia,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be as essentiall to His Crown, as the other is but a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that not usuall, nor in debate.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>That Returns should not bee made against England upon their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Declarations, as if they were Obligations, whereas they were alterable at pleasure, that Arguments were urged with as great instancy, as at</hi> Ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge <hi>for the Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:179544:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Our Preface and State of the Question answers the last part abundantly and cleareth, that we are now debating for that, which all the Declarations of the Parliament, &amp; their Comissioners at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> did plead for, to wit, That the <hi>Militia</hi> be joyntly in the Crown and the Parliament, and we still oppose that which we opposed at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> to be in the King alone: And what we speak for the Crown, is out of Conscience of our Covenant with God, and publick Declarations to the World, for the good of both Kingdoms, and from no other Motive, nor for any other End; And so we should bee as zealous and tender as any, who may doe the same thing or the contrary, from other principles and for other ends. But in Answer to the first Part, That we do not take upon us to judge of your Laws, but of the Declarations made to the World, and made to us in a speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all manner, that we might judge of them, beleeve them, and ingage in the war accordingly, which we having done, and suffered so much thereby, cannot in reason admit them to bee so alterable at pleasure, because that the Houses therein told us, they would live and die in that quarrell, that they declared the same to other Nations, that they conjured all who had Christianity or Charity to beleeve them, that many times they attested the Name of God to the truth of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, and sincerity of those their intentions, That they declared this was the greatest Obligation, That a Christian, and most solemn publick faith, that a State or Parliament could give; That no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian or Brother could misbeleeve a Parliament, so declaring, so protesting, and so swearing; That no trouble or successe should change their resolutions; That they made these Declarations to deceive none, but to undeceive all men, lest they should be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the contrary aspersions. And as the Honourable Houses doe expect, that their Declarations for the future shall bee imbraced, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, and rested upon; so wee doubt not they will tender the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Credit of their former Declarations, which if they should bee violated (as God forbid, and wee trust will bee far from their thoughts) the Houses in their Wisdome will foresee what influence and reflection this might have upon their present and following De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, the former being of as great Authority, and confirmed with as high Asseverations as any of the future are like to bee; So that wee cannot beleeve that ever the Wisdome, Piety, Loyalty, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, Faithfulnesse, and Constancy of the Houourable Houses, will ever suffer them to comply, or joyn issue with any such Principles, or Intentions of any Parties or Persons (whatsoever they be) as tend to the introducing of an Arbitrary Alterability of so reall Dueties, founded upon so firm foundations, in relation to God, this Church and State, and Union of the Kingdomes, and of so solemn Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, backed with such Attestations and Oaths, upon any motives or changes whatsoever, which are no good Interpreters of former Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants and Declarations: All which Reasons, Answers, and Replyes, with the annexed Papers of some particular Citations, out of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Collection of the Declarations of the Honourable Houses, wee offer unto their serious Consideration.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="paper">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:179544:14"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PAPER, Delivered in to the Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Commissioners of SCOTLAND: <hi>Containing the Citations of severall Passages out of the severall Declarations of the Houses, concerning the</hi> MILITIA, <hi>and niformity in Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> we desire the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Passages to be considered, as they are cited out of the Declarations made by the Honourable Houses, and published to the World, in the exact Collection of Remonstrances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Order of the House of Commons; wherein our Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is only to shew the grounds of our Scruples, the reasons of our former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and the motives of our Confidence, that the Honourable Houses will rest satisfied with what wee have now offered; and wee desire that no other Inference or Construction bee put upon our Papers and Citations, especially sith wee are most ready and willing upon Information, to rectifie any mistake, explain our meaning, and so farre as is in our Power to prevent misun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 59. <hi>Pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Pag.</hi> 80. Containeth three Petitions of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houses to the King, to put the Forces and the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome into the hands of such Persons as the Parliament might confide in, and as should bee recommended to His Majestie by both Houses: And <hi>pag.</hi> 73. containeth the Names of the Persons recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the Houses to His Majestie. The same, and no more was craved from His Majesty, in the Treaty at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 89. (in regard His Majestie did not grant their Petitions) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179544:14"/>the Ordinance of both Houses, for ordering the <hi>Militia,</hi> giving power to such and such to suppresse all Rebellions, Insurrections, and Invasions, according as they shall receive Directions by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Authority, signified by both Houses of Parliament unto them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 93. <hi>pag.</hi> 95. <hi>pag.</hi> 96. <hi>pag.</hi> 100. Especially <hi>pag.</hi> 112. <hi>pag.</hi> 172. and 173. containeth the justification of that Ordinance, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging the Lieges by the fundamentall Laws of the Kingdome, in the case of extreme danger found by the Parliament, and His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties refusall to consent to the remedy thereof; and in all these votes this is made an extraordinary case, distinct from the ordinary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is further cleered by the resolution of the Question, how to understand the Laws concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> published <hi>pag.</hi> 150.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 126. and <hi>pag.</hi> 158, and 159. The Kings Majesty complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that He could not in Honour nor Justice consent unto it, because they thereby exclude Him from any Power or Authority in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position and execution of the <hi>Militia</hi> together with them, and that for a time utterly unlimited. It is answered by the Honourable Houses (beside the limitation of the time to two or three years) <hi>pag.</hi> 206. that there is nothing in the body of the Ordinance that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes His Royall Authority, in the disposing or execution of it; but only it is provided, that it should be signified by both Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as that Channel through which it will be best derived, and most certainly to those ends for which it is intended; and let all the World judge whether they have not reason to insist upon it, that the strength of the Kingdome should rather be ordered, according to the direction or advice of the Great Counsell of the Land, equally intrusted by the King and by the Kingdome, then that the safety of the King, Parliament and Kingdome should be left at the devotion of a few unknown Counsellours, many of them not intrusted at all by the King in any publike way, nor at all confided in by the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And <hi>pag.</hi> 701. But a trust cannot bee recalled or destroyed at pleasure. Wee say so too; and that wee have neither destroyed nor invaded that of His Majesties, because we directed it in the right way, and to the right ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 155. and 167. and <hi>pag.</hi> 437. the Kings Majestie urgeth, and presseth the Statute, <hi>Anno</hi> 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. That the Subjects by the Duety (or Oath) of Alleageance are bound to serve the Prince in His wars, for the defence of Him and the Land, against every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Power, and Might reared against Him: And Statute 11. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. That every Subject by the duety of Alleageance, is bound to assist the King at all seasons, when need shall require, and severall other Lawes there cited. The Parliament in their Answers, <hi>pag.</hi> 280 and 725. and 729. granteth it to be duety of Alleageance to serve the King in wars, for the defence of Him and of the Land, but not in wars against the Land, or the Parliament, the representative body thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 268. In the Kings Oath of Coronation, He promiseth <hi>justas
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179544:15"/>Leges, ac Consuetudines per Eum esse protegendas:</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 290. Hee argueth, Can it be imagined that He should be bound by Oath to passe such Lawes (and such a Law is the Bill they brought to us of the <hi>Militia</hi>) as should put the Power wherewith Hee is trusted, out of Himself, in the hands of other men, and divest and disable Him of all possible Power to perform the great businesse of the Oath, which is to protect them: If we give away all our Power, or if it bee taken from us, we can not protect any man; And what discharge would it be for us, either before God or man (when our good Subjects, whom God and the Law hath committed to our charge, shall bee worryed and spoiled) to say that we trusted others to protect them, that is, To do that duety for us, which is essentially and inseparably our own.</p>
            <p>Whereunto the Parliament answereth, <hi>pag.</hi> 710. For that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken from the matter of His Oath, that it cannot bee meant that the King should be thereby obliged to divest Himself of a Power to protect His Subjects, which is the great businesse of that Oath: If He had said (as we did not) that the King had beene bound to passe all Bils that should be offered to Him by both Houses of Parliament, without any limitation, or qualification of Reason and Justice, yet such a supposition as this could not fall upon a Parliament, as if they could desire such a thing, much lesse that a King were oblieged for to grant it: But how unproperly this is applyed to our Bill concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> wee leave it to every man for to judge, when they shall consider how necessary, how just, and how reasonable that Bill was, and how much they mistake the way and the manner wherein His Majestie is to protect His Subjects, that have advised Him to deny that Bill, and to set up a Commission of Array, so destructive to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and to the propriety of the Subject, was it not necessary that the Kingdome should be put unto a posture of Defence: On all hands it is agreed, the People petitioned for it, the Parliament maketh it a ground of their Ordinance; The King maketh it a ground of His Commissions, all the Question is concerning the way, and wee shall make it good; That the main Point wherein His Majestie differed from us in the Bill concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> was this, That wee desired the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> should bee put into the hands of Persons approved by His Majestie, and both Houses, to be answerable to the Law for discharge of their dueties; and His Majestie would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of it, unlesse He might bee Judge, both of the time when, the cause why, and the manner how, that Power should bee exercised, and that in His owne Person out of His Courts, for in them Hee might have called them to an accompt for not doing, or doing what they should have done or not have done: and if it is by the Law, and by the Courts of Justice, judging of the Law, and by the <hi>Militia,</hi> to maintain the proceedings in them according to Law, that His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie is to protect His Subjects: Our Bill for the <hi>Militia</hi> was so far from divesting Him of that Power, that it did give Him a Power (which He had not legally before) to command the whole <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdom in an orderly and effectuall way; and all these to whom
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179544:15"/>it was committed to obey and assist Him, in the Protection of all His good Subjects, in their Persons and Estates, according to Law: And <hi>pag.</hi> 715. as concerning making of Lawes, so of the commanding of the <hi>Militia.</hi> The Parliament argueth, To what end a trust in the King, and His Oath to perform this trust, if it might bee done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise? But yet that in discharge thereof, the King ought to attribute much to the judgement of His Parliament: It were strange then for ever to seclude the Crown from doing that (by the advice of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) which falleth within the Oath of Coronation, and the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience whereunto falleth within the Oath of Alleagance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 301. renued in 368, 369, 370, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The King urgeth severall Statutes, especially the seventh year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the first. The Parliament affirmeth, That to the King it belongeth, and His Part it is by His Royall Seigneory streightly to defend wearing of Armes, and all other forces against the Peace, at all times when it shall please Him, and to punish him that shall doe contrary, according to the Lawes and Usages of the Realm; And heereunto all Subjects are bound to aid the King as their Soveraign Lord, at all occasions when need shall bee. The Parliament answereth heereunto as followeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 303. and 304. That neither the Statute 7. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. therein vouched, nor any other Law in this Kingdome doth restrain or make void the Ordinance agreed upon by both Houses of Parliament, for the ordering and disposing the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome, in this time of extreme and imminent danger, nor expose His Majesties Subjects to any punishment for obeying the same, notwithstanding that His Majestie hath refused to give His Consent to that Ordinance, but ought to bee obeyed by the fundamentall Lawes of this Kingdome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that the Question is not whether it belong to the King or not to restrain such force; but if the King shall refuse to discharge that Duety and Trust, whether there is not a Power in the two Houses to provide for the safety of the Parliament, and Peace of the Kingdom, which is the end for which the Ordinance concerning the <hi>Militia</hi> was made; and being agreeable to the scope and purpose of the Law, cannot in reason be adjudged to be contrary to it: For although the Law do confirm it to bee in the King, (and <hi>pag.</hi> 727. the Law hath placed in His Person the power to protect all other persons, and <hi>pag.</hi> 908. they promise to Him Subjection, as the correlate of His Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them, which the Houses craves from Him) and the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament upon the Treaty at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1643 acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the same; yet it doth not exclude those in whom the Law hath placed a Power for that purpose, as in the Courts of Justice, that Sheriffs and other Officers and Ministers of these Courts, and as their Power is derived from the King by His Patents, yet it cannot bee restrained by His Majesties Command, much lesse the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, because the Authority thereof is of an higher and more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent nature then any of those Courts.</p>
            <p>It is acknowledged that the King is fountain of Justice and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but the acts of Justice and protection are not exercised in his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179544:16"/>own person, nor depend upon his pleasure, but by his Courts, and by his Ministers, who must do their dutie therein, though the King in his own person should forbid them: and therefore if judgements should be given by them against the Kings will and personall command, yet are they the Kings judgements.</p>
            <p>Pag. 207. The Parliament being often urged by his Majestie to shew him their fundamental Laws which warranted them to settle the <hi>Militia</hi> in the case of extreame danger and his refusall, they set down their Votes, and the fundamentall Law warranting the same, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. That in this case of extreame danger and his Majesties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusall, the Ordinance of Parliament agreed upon by both Houses for the <hi>Militia,</hi> doth obliege the people, and ought to be obeyed by the fundamentall Laws of this Kingdom: For it doth appear that there is no colour of this Tax, that we go about to introduce a new Law, much lesse to exercis ean arbitrary power, but indeed to prevent it; for this Law is as old as the Kingdom; That the Kingdom must not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a means to preserve it self; Which that it may be done without confusion, This nation hath intrusted certain hands with a power to provide in an orderly and regular way, for the good and safety of the whole, which power by the constitution of this Kingdom, is in his Majestie, and in his Parliament together. Yet since the Prince being but one person, is more subject to accidents of nature and chance, whereby the Common-wealth may be deprived of the fruit of that trust which was in part imposed in him: in cases of such necessity, that the Kingdom may not be enforced to return to its first Principles, &amp; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man left to do what is right in his own eyes, without either guide or Rule, The wisdom of this State hath intrusted the Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with a power to supply what shall be wanting on the part of the Prince; As is evident by the constant custome and practise there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, In cases of Non-age, naturall disability, and captivity; and the like reason doth and must hold for the exercise of the same power, in such cases where the Royall trust cannot be, or is not discharged, and that the Kingdome runs an evident and imminent danger thereby, which danger having been declared by the Lords and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there needs not the authority of any person or Court to affirm, nor is it in the power of any person or Court to revoke the judgement.</p>
            <p>By the fundamentall Law, frame, and constitution of the Kingdom, the ordinary government is settled and intrusted to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and cannot be changed without the subverting the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws. And that onely in extraordinary cases of extreame danger, and the Kings incapacity or refusall to discharge his trust, The Houses <hi>pro salute populi, cujus salus lex suprema,</hi> may direct, and dispose of the <hi>Militia.</hi> But by the last Proposition, the extraordinary case becometh the ordinary Government, (to wit, perpetuall, and in the time of peace) and that which was since the foundation of this Kingdom, the ordinary Government, is not to be so much as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary case.</p>
            <p>The King in many of his Declarations, and for instance Pag. 298.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179544:16"/>urgeth, that hereby the Houses desired not onely the ruine of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but of Monarchie it self, which was more then ever was offered to any of his Predecessors, &amp;c. The Parliament in their Duply hereto Pag. 730. justly set down what followeth, as a doctrine which deserves to be branded with the marks of perpetual scorn and indignation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the representative body of the whole Kingdom is a faction of Malignant, Schismaticall, and ambitious Persons, whose Designe is and alwayes hath been to alter the whole frame of Government both of Church and State, and to subject both King and People to their lawlesse and arbitrary Power and Government, and that they designe the ruine of His Majesties Person, and of Monarchy it self; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently that they are Traitors, and all the Kingdome with them, (for their act is the act of the whole Kingdome) and whether their punishment and ruine may not also involve the whole Kingdome in conclusion, and reduce it into the condition of a conquered Nation, No man can tell, but Experience sheweth us, that Successe often draweth men not onely beyond their Professions, but also many times beyond their first Intentions.</p>
            <p>And in many other places the Parliament answereth this aspersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and giveth assurances to the contrary both to His Majestie and to the world, as <hi>pag.</hi> 100. that as they behooved upon His Majesties refusall to settle the <hi>Militia,</hi> to secure and preserve His Majestie and the Kingdomes from extreame danger; so they still resolve to keep themselves within the bounds of Faithfulnesse and Alleageance to His Majesties sacred Person and Crown: And <hi>ibidem</hi> they say thus, Whereas Your Majestie is pleased to say, That for Your Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence neer the Parliament, You wish it might bee so Safe and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that You had no cause to absent Your self from <hi>Whitehall.</hi> This wee take as the greatest breach of the priviledge of Parliament that can bee offered, as the heaviest misery to your self, and imputation upon us that can bee imagined, and the most mischievous effect of evill counsels: It roots up the strongest foundation of the Safety and Honour which your Crown affoords; It seemes as much as may bee to cast upon the Parliament such a charge as is inconsistent with the nature of that Great Councell, being the Body whereof Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie is the Head: It strikes at the very Beeing both of King and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, depriving Your Majestie in Your own Apprehension of their Fidelity, and them of Your Protection, which are the mutuall Bonds and Supports of Government and Subjection.</p>
            <p>Wee have according to Your Majesties Desire laid our hand upon our hearts, wee have askt our selves in the strictest examination of our consciences, wee have searcht our affections, our thoughts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered our actions, and wee can finde none that can give Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie any just occasion to absent Your Self from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, But that You may with more Honour and Safety continue there then in any other place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 195. At the entry of their Declaration, May 19. the infinite Mercy and Providence of God, hath bin abundantly manifested since
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179544:17"/>the beginning of this Parliament, in great variety of Protections and Blessings, whereby He hath not only delivered us from many wicked Plots and Designes; which if they had taken effect, would have brought ruine upon this Kingdome: But out of those attempts hath produced diverse evident and remarkable Advantages to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of these services, which wee have beene desirous to perform to our Soveraigne the King, and to this Church and State, in provy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the publike peace and prosperity of His Majestie, and all His Realms, which in the presence of the same Al-seeing Deity, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test to have beene, and still to be the only end of all our Councels and Endeavours, wherein wee have resolved to continue freed and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from all private aimes, personall respects, or passions whatsoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 203, 204. Wee are resolved, The gracious favour of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie expressed in that Bill, for the continuance of this Parliament, and the advantage and security which wee have thereby, from beeing dissolved, shall not encourage us to doe any thing, which otherwise had not beene fit to have beene done; and wee are ready to make it good before all the world, that although His Majestie hath passed many Bills very advantagious for the Subject, yet in none of them have wee bereaved His Majestie of any just, necessary, or profitable prerogative of the Crown.</p>
            <p>Wee so earnestly desire His Majesties return to <hi>London,</hi> that upon it wee conceive depends the very safety and being of both His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and therefore we must protest, that as for the time past, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Government of <hi>London,</hi> nor the Laws of the Land, have lost their life or force for His Security: so for the future we shall be ready to say or doe any thing, that may stand with the Duety or Honour of a Parliament, which may raise a mutuall confidence betwixt His Majestie and us, as wee do wish, and as the affairs of this Kingdome doe require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 281. We shall conclude, That although these wicked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours about His Majestie, have presumed under His Majesties Name, to put that dishonour and affront upon both Houses of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, as to make them the countenancers of Treason, enough to have dissolved all the bonds and sinewes of mutuall confidence betwixt His Majestie and His Parliament (of whom the <hi>Maxime</hi> of the Law is, that a dishonourable thing ought not to bee imagined of them) yet we doubt not, but it shall in the end appear before all the World, that our endeavours have beene most hearty and sincere for the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the true Protestant Religion, the Kings Just Perogative, the Lawes and Liberties of the Land, and the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, In which endeavours by the grace of God we will still persist, though we should perish in the work, which if it should be, it is much to bee feared; That, Religion, Lawes, Liberties, and Parliaments, would not be long-lived after us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 307. Your Majesties most humble and faithfull Subjects ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing in their thoughts &amp; desires, more precious and of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er esteeme (next to the immediate Honour and Service of God) then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179544:17"/>the just and faithfull performance of their duety to your Majesty and this Kingdome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>pag.</hi> 282. The King alleadgeth some speaches in the Houses to the prejudice of the Royall Branches, The Parliament ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly answereth <hi>pag.</hi> 696. this, and although they would perswade His Majesty, that there is little confidence to bee placed in our modesty and duety; Yet as God is witnesse of our thoughts, so shall our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, witnesse to all the World, That to the honour of Religion, and of those that are most zealous in it (so much stricken at by the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of that Declaration under odious names) wee shall suffer more from, and for our Soveraign, then we hope, God will ever permit the malice of wicked Councellors to put us to. And though the happinesse of this and all Kingdomes dependeth chiefly upon God, yet wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that it doth so mainly depend upon His Majesty, and the Royall Branches of that Root, That as we have heretofore, so we shall hereafter esteeme no Hazard too great, no reproach too vile, but that we shall willingly goe through the one, and undergoe the other; That we and the whole Kingdome may enjoy that happinesse, which we cannot in an Ordinary way of providence expect from any other Fountaine, or Streames then those from whence (were the poison of evill Councell once removed from about them) wee doubt not but wee and the whole Kingdome should bee satisfied most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 728. We never suffered that word of deposing the King to goe out of our mouths, nor the thing to enter in our thoughts, nor can it be collected out of any thing we have said. And now for the Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wherewith we are said to assault His Majestie, and endeavour to divest Him of all his Royall rights and dignities; We doubt not but we shall make it appear to all the World that what may seeme highest in our Propositions, hath beene in effect asked and obtained by our Predecessours before us, and by our Nieghbours beside us, and that we have more reason to ask it and to obtaine it, then either the one or the other, and yet to testifie to all the World how much wee desire peace, and to avoid the miseries and confusion of a civill Warre, wee have not, nor shall insist upon any thing, but what we hold necessary for preservation of the safety and peace of the Kingdome, and for the securitie of our Religion and Liberties, and these good Lawes which we already have, and hope farther to obtaine by the frequent meeting and free sitting of Parliaments: And as we have bin careful to decline all appearance of any private respects in them to our selves; So wee having the Honour of God, and of His Majesty, and the Peace, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Prosperity of this Kingdome, chiefly before our eyes in these our Propositions and in all our actions, we rest assured, that both God and Man will abhor and abominate that monstruous and most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious charge laid upon the representative body of this Kingdom, of designing the ruine not only of his Majesties person, but of Monarchie it self. And we appeal to all the World, whether worse words then these can bee given? And whether wee may not justly expect the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179544:18"/>worst actions that the malice and power of the Malignant Party about His Majesty can produce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 750. GOD who sees our innocency, and that we have no aimes, but at his glory, and the publike good, will (we hope) free your Majesty from these destructive Councells, who labour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their own power by Blood and Rapine: And blesse our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, who seek nothing but to procure and establish the Honourable Peace and safety of your Majestie and Kingdomes, upon the sure foundation of Religion and Justice.</p>
            <p>The Declarations after mentioned were sent from the Parliament of England to the Kingdome of Scotland, to inform them of the true state of the quarrell and cause of the war, and to perswade them to ingage with them therein, which they did accordingly.</p>
            <p>The King by His Letter of the 20 of May, 1642. to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Scotland, declared His great sufferings from His Parliament, and that Hee was only maintaining His Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is inserted in the <hi>pag.</hi> 255. Thereupon the Parliament emitts a Declaration, and sends it to Scotland, assuring them by Protestation, that His Majesties sufferings come not from any intention or action of theirs, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with all fidelity to procure the happinesse of His Majestie and of His Kingdome: And that they should doe their best endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to promote the Honour, Wealth, and Prosperity of Scotland (because of our great affection and respect to them at that time, upon believing their Declarations) and preserve their Union, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>pag.</hi> 330.</p>
            <p>In August 1643. The Parliament sends down Colonel <hi>Pickering</hi> to the Generall Assembly, with a Declaration to them, shewing, that they thought fit to send them a coppy of their Supplication to His Majestie, (wherewith hee brought also other Declarations, and gave them to the Lords of the Secret Counsell, and Conservators of Peace) That, that Church and Kingdome (whereunto they are tied by so many and so neer bonds, both civil and spirituall) may see that the like mind is now in them, that formerly appeared to be in the Nation; and that they were tender of bloud, and zealous for a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Church and State, which if not interrupted by war, they would settle, to the encrease of His Majesties Honour and State, the peace and prosperity of this Kingdome; and especially to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, by the advancement of the true Religion, and such a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Church, as shall bee most agreeable to Gods Word: Out of all which there will also result a most firm and stable Union betweene the two Kingdomes, which according to our Protestation we shall by all good wayes and means, upon all occasions, labour to preserve and maintain.</p>
            <p>The Supplication which hee brought, was that which was sent after nomination of my Lord <hi>Essex</hi> Generall, <hi>pag.</hi> 465. having that expression, That Hee would return to His Parliament, and hearken to their faithfull Advices, and humble Petitions, which should only bee for advancing Religion, His own Royall Honour and Safety, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179544:18"/>preservation of our Lawes and Liberties; and they should punish and prevent all tumultuous and seditious actions, speeches and writings, which might give him any just cause of distance, or apprehension of danger, from which publike aimes and resolutions, no sinister or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat respect shall ever make them decline; That they should settle the <hi>Militia</hi> by a Bill, in such a way as shall bee honourable and safe for His Majestie, most agreeable to the duety of Parliament, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for the good of the Kingdome, that the security thereof bee not for its destruction; with which if His Majesties Counsels and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses shall concur, we doubt not but we shall quickly make it appear to the world, by the most eminent effects of love and duety, That His Majesties Personal safety, Royall Honour and Greatnes are much dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to us then our lives and fortunes, which wee do most heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, and shall most willingly imploy, for the support and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof. They again repeat the same, <hi>pag.</hi> 509. as the firm and constant resolution, to witnesse their unshaken and constant loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; and that they would make Him and His Posterity as much beloved at home, and feared abroad, as any Prince that ever swayed this Scepter.</p>
            <p>They renew and enlarge the same in their Petition, the 11. of September, <hi>pag.</hi> 587. and offers to His Majestie, security, honour, service, obedience, support, and other effects of an humble, loyall, and faithfull Subjection; and seek nothing, but that our Religion, Liberty, Peace of the Kingdome, and Safety of the Parliament may bee secured from the open violence and cunning practises of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked party; and as wee never gave Your Majestie any just cause of withdrawing Your Self from Your Great Councell, so it hath ever been, and shall ever be far from us, to give any impediment to Your Majesties returne, or to neglect any proper meanes of curing the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers of the Kingdome, and closing the dangerous breaches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Your Majesty and Your Parliament, according to the great trust which lyes upon us; And if Your Majesty shall now be pleased to come back to your Parliament without your forces, we shall be ready to secure Your Royall Person, Crowne and Dignity with our lives and fortunes, Your Presence in this great Councell, being the only meanes of any Treaty betwixt Your Majesty and them, with hope of successe.</p>
            <p>And in none of our desires to Your Majesty shall we be swayed by any particular mans advantage, but shall give a cleare testimony to Your Majestie and the whole World, That in all things done by us, we faithfully intend the good of Your Majesty, and of Your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and that we will not bee delivered from this end, by any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or selfe respects whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Againe they renew the same, <hi>pag.</hi> 618. Shewing that they have for the just and necessary defence for the Protestant Religion, of Your Majesties Person, Crown and Dignity, of the Lawes, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of this Kingdome, and the Priviledges and Power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Taken up Armes and appointed and authorized <hi>Robert</hi> Earle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179544:19"/>of <hi>Essex</hi> to bee Captaine Generall, wherein if Your Majestie please to yeeld to our most humble and earnest desires, We do in the presence of Almighty God professe, that we wil receive Your Majestie with all Honour, yeeld you all due obedience and subjection, and faithfullie endeavour to secure Your Person and Estate from all dangers, and to the uttermost of our power, to procure and establish to Your Selfe and Your People, all the blessings of a glorious and happie Reigne.</p>
            <p>He delivered also the Votes of the 12 of July, <hi>pag.</hi> 457. of raising an Army for the safety of the Kings Person, defence of the Parliament, and preserving Religion, Lawes, Lives, and Peace of the Kingdom, and to die and live with the Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> in that Cause, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Petition appointed to be framed.</p>
            <p>He delivered likewise the Declarations, <hi>pag.</hi> 458. wherein the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament expresseth, that in all their endeavours, they intend wholly the advancement of His Majesties Honour and Safety, And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainment of the ancient (though of late yeares much invaded) Rights, Lawes, and Liberties, being the Birth-right of the Subjects of this Land, and settling of the true Protestant Religion (the glory of their Nation) in Peace and Purity.</p>
            <p>He delivered the Declaration, <hi>pag.</hi> 461. concerning the distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Kingdome (wherein the King breaking his Declarations is challenged) they desire all mens assistance in this necessary defensive Warre, And that they shall in all their proceedings manifest, they are carryed by no respects but of the publike good; That alteration of Religion is the maine end of their Enemies, which will draw on losse of Liberty, and subversion of Law; so it rests only, Whether free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born English-men will adhere to King and Parliament, or to the King seduced by Jesuites and Cavaliers.</p>
            <p>In their reply to the King, <hi>pag.</hi> 473. they shew the reason why they tooke into their custody the Town of Hull, the Magazine and Navy, passed the Ordinance of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and made preparation of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, was for the security of Religion, the safety of His Majesties Person, of the Kingdome and Parliament, all which they did see in evident and imminent danger, from which when they shall bee secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that the forces of the Kingdome shall not bee used to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction thereof, They shall then bee ready to withdraw the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son out of Hull, to deliver the Magazine and Navy, And settle the <hi>Militia</hi> by Bill, in such a way, as shall be Honourable and Sa fefor His Majestie, most agreeable to the duety of Parliament, and effectuall for the good of the Kingdome, as they have profest in their late Petition: And as for the laying down of Armes, when the causes which moved them to provide for the defence of His Majestie, the Kingdome and Parliament, shall be taken away, they shall very willingly and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forbear any farther preparations, and lay down their force alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy raised.</p>
            <p>He delivered also the Declaration, <hi>pag.</hi> 491. giving an accompt to the World of the Justice of their proceedings, and to warne them all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179544:19"/>to concurre, They complain, that the designe of their Enemies is, to alter the constitution and frame of this Government both in Church and State: That they begunne with Scotland by the Service Book; For well they knew the same fate attended both Kingdomes; And Religion could not be altered in the one, without altering it in the other, and Religion is there called The life of our lives.</p>
            <p>And seeing now the Question is so clearly stated: They invite all to assist for the preservation of Religion, the King and our Selves, And that it appeareth that it is neither <hi>Hull,</hi> nor Magazine, nor <hi>Militia,</hi> which are grounds of the Warre, whereupon they conclude their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to the World, That they the Lords and Commons were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to expose their Lives and Fortunes for Maintenance of the true Religion, the Kings Person, Honour and Estate, Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and Right and Liberties of Subjects, and for prevention of alteration of Religion; And requireth all who have sense of Pietie, Honour, or Compasson, to help a distressed State, especially such as have taken the Protestation, and are bound in this same duety with us unto their God, their King and Countrey, to come to their assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, This being the true Cause for which we raise an Army under the Earle of <hi>Essex,</hi> with whom wee will live and die in this quarrell. This is sent to Scotland with Colonell <hi>Pickering,</hi> is read to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly, Lords of Councell, and Conservators of Peace, and beleeved there.</p>
            <p>In all the Letters and Declarations from the Conservators of Peace in Scotland, there is a cleare evidence of our earnest pressing Unity in Religion and Peace, with all respect and tendernesse to His Majesties Authority, and the Subjects Liberty. And the Parliament of England the 20. of October 1642. doth answere, that they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to concurre in all good wayes for the Kings Honour and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and Unity between the Kingdomes: And generally in all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of the Houses sent to Scotland, They expresse their desire for uniformity, and preservation of His Majesties Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 663. The Declaration and Protestation of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to this Kingdom, and to the whole World, October 22. 1642. We, in presence of Almighty God, for the satisfaction of our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and the discharge of our great trust, protest and declare, That no private passion or respect, or evill intention to His Majesties Person, no designe to the prejudice of his just Honour and Authority, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged us to take Armes and raise Forces, And wee have alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired from our Soules, manifested in our Proceedings, Petitions, and Remonstrances to His Majesty, professed our loyaltie and obedience to his Crowne, readinesse and resolution to defend his Person and support his Estate, with our lives and fortunes to the uttermost of our power.</p>
            <p>They remember a petition sent, <hi>pag.</hi> 587. Wherein they professe in the sight of Almighty God, which is the strongest obligation that any Christian, and the most solemne publike Faith, which any such State as a Parliament can give: That we would receive him with all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179544:20"/>Honour, yeeld him all true obedience and subjection, and defend his Person and Estate; That in this cause and defence thereof, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the concurrence of Scotland, according to the Act of Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And which safety of Religion, Lawes, and Liberties, We do here againe professe before the everliving God, to be the chief end of all our Councells, and Resolutions, without any intention or desire to hurt or injure his Majesty, either in his Person or just Power. This Declaration was sent to the Conservators of Peace, with their safe conduct, and delivered by Colonell <hi>Pickering</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>In the Declaration to the World, <hi>pag.</hi> 657. sent to Scotland con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the allegations, That the Army is raised to murther or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the King; wee hoped any that professed the name of a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, could not have so little Charity as to raise such a scandall, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they must needs know the Protestation taken by every member of both Houses, whereby they promise in presence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, to defend His Majesties Person: The Promise and Protestation made by the members of both Houses, upon the nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Generall to live and die with him, wherein is expressed, That this Army was raised for the defence of the Kings Person; Our earnest addresses and humble petitions to His Majesty, to remove his Royall Person from that Army, A request inconsistent with any purpose to offer the least violence to his Person, which hath and ever shall be dear unto us: That their Religion and Liberties being secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto them, they shall willingly disband. To the imputation of their intention to change the Government, they answere, That the Army is raised for the Lands necessary preservation.</p>
            <p>The Declaration to the Estates of <hi>Holland, pag.</hi> 635. declareth the question betweene the King and Parliament, Is not whether Hee shall enjoy the same Prerogative and Power, which hath belonged to our former Kings, His Royall Predecessors; But whether that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative and Power shall bee used to our defence or ruine, and we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing from Him but security and protection from those mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievouous designes multiplied against them.</p>
            <p>But above all, remember the Declaration, 7. November, <hi>pag.</hi> 737. directed and sent to the Kingdome of Scotland, and delivered to that State by Colonel <hi>Pickering,</hi> mentioning, that Scotland had lovingly invited them to a neerer and higher degree of Union, in matters of Religion, and Church Government, which we have most willingly and affectually embraced, and intend to pursue: And though we seek nothing from his Majestie, that may diminish his just authority or honour, and have by many humble Petitions endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to put an end to this unnaturall war and combustion, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure His protection and security, for our Religion, Liberties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (according to that great trust His Majestie is bound to by the Lawes of the Land) and shall continue to renew our Petitions in that kinde, wee are necessitated to stand upon our just defence, and to seek the speedy and powerfull assiance of our Brethren, according to the Act of Pacification, common duety of Christianity, and particular
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179544:20"/>Interest of their own Nation, which would produce preservation of Religion, Honour, Safety, and Peace to His Majestie and Subjects, and a more strict conjunction of the Councels, Designes, and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of both Nations, for the relief of the reformed Churches: All which we did believe, and desire to see observed, and did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Kings Answer thereunto, immediatly sent to Scotland a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, as intending to countenance Sects and Schismes, and to subvert His Royall Authority.</p>
            <p>Wee could cite to your Lordships as many of our Declarations to the same sense, which wee acknowledge as obligatory, and so need not to repeat them.</p>
            <p>But that which sticks most with us, are the Oaths taken, first <hi>sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratim</hi> by both these Nations, and then <hi>conjunctim</hi> in the last solemn League and Covenant between the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Wee need neither set down our first Covenant, nor the Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is so short, cleer, and known to all, <hi>viz.</hi> To defend and maintain, according to the duety of my Alleagance, His Majesties Royall Person, Honour, and State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in all just and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wayes, to preserve the Union and Peace between the Kingdoms, and neither for hope, fear, or other respect relinquish the promise, vow, and Protestation, which whosoever would not take, was voted to be unfit to bear office in Church or State, whereunto our Oath of Parliament is paralell almost <hi>in iisdem verbis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the late solemn League and Covenant, wee may not forget the Act of the Generall Assembly of Scotland, and of the Convention of Estates, 17 August, 1643. approving of the first draught of it, as the most powerfull mean, by the blessing of God, for settling and preserving the true Protestant Religion, with perfect Peace in His Majesties Dominions, and propagating the same to other Nations, and for establishing his Maiesties Throne to all Ages and Generations, and recommending it in these termes to the Kingdome of England; and which is most fully twise or thrise expressed in their Declaration, then sent to the Houses, and in their Answer to the Divines.</p>
            <p>Like as the two Acts of the Commissioners of the Assembly, and Committee of Estates, in October, 1643. approving the same (after the return therof from England) in the same terms, and appoint it so to be sworn and subscribed: Whereupon the Covenant having these Acts prefixed, was subscribed and sworn in a most solemn manner by the Commissioners of both Kingdoms, at Edinburgh, and one Principall so subscribed, Delivered by us to the English Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and another from them to us, to be keeped <hi>in retentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewise the Ordinance of the Honourable Houses, for the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing of the Covenant, prefixed an Exhortation, and therein affirmeth.</p>
            <p>For what is there almost in this Covenant, which was not for sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance either expressed, or manifestly included in that solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179544:21"/>of May 5. 1641. wherein the whole Kingdome stands in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged untill this day: The sinfull neglect whereof doth (as we may justly fear) open a Floud-gate, the more to let in all these calamities upon the Kingdome, and cast upon it a necessity of renewing Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and of entring into this.</p>
            <p>If it bee pleaded, That this Covenant crosseth the Oathes of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Alleageance, there can be nothing further from Truth; for this Covenant binds all, and more strongly engageth them to preserve and defend the Kings Majesties Person and Authority, in the Preservation and Defence of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>The Covenant it self, both in the Title and in the Preamble, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe the three mayn Motives, Dueties, and Ends thereof, whereof the second is the Honour and Happinesse of the King and His Posterity.</p>
            <p>In the third Article, wee shall with the same sincerity, reality, and constancy in our severall vocations, endeavour with our Estates and Lives, mutually to preserve the Rights and Priviledges of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments and the Liberties of the Kingdomes, And to preserve and defend the Kings Majesties Person and Authority, in the preservation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdomes. That the world may bear witnesse with our consciences of our loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminish His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties just Power and Greatnesse.</p>
            <p>In the fourth, we shall discover evill instruments, by hindering the reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his people, or one of the Kingdomes from another, or making any parties among the people contrary to this League and Covenant.</p>
            <p>In the fifth, And whereas the happines of a blessed peace between these Kingdomes, Denied in former times to our Progenitors, is by the good providence of God granted unto us, and hath beene late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded and settled by both Parliaments; Wee shall each one of us according to our power and interest, indeavour that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conjoyned in a firme Peace and Union to all posterity, And that justice may be done upon the wilfull opposers thereof, in manner expressed in the precedent Articles.</p>
            <p>Now this firm Union between them settled by both Parliaments, and to bee continued by that Article; as also by the Protestation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, and our Oath of Parliament, is expressed in the Act of Pacification in the large Treaty, <hi>in his verbis,</hi> That the great ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of a constant and friendly Conjunction of the two Kingdomes, now united by Alleageance and loyall Subjection, to one Soveraigne and Head, may be firmly observed, and continued to all posterity.</p>
            <p>In the sixth Article wee may not make defection to the contrary part, or give our selves to a detestable indifferency or neutrality in this cause, which so much concerneth the Glory of God, good of the Kingdomes, and Honour of the King, but all our dayes zealous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179544:21"/>and constantly promote it against all opposition and impediments; all which we shall do as in the fight of God, and perform all Dueties we owe to God and man, and make this Covenant in the presence of Almighty God the Searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the same, as we shall answer at the great Day.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot but remember the first Article of the Treaty between the Kingdomes, <hi>viz.</hi> It is agreed and concluded, that the Covenant represented to the Convention of Estates, and Generall Assembly of Scotland, and sent to both Houses of the Parliament of England, in the same form as it is now returned from the two Houses of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England to their Brethren of Scotland, and allowed by the Committee of Estates, and Committee of the Generall Assembly, be sworn and subscribed by both Kingdoms, as a most neer tye and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction betwixt them, for their mutuall defence against the Papist and Prelaticall Faction, and their Adherents in both Kingdomes, and for pursuance of the ends exprest in the Covenant; and that the rest of the Articles are expresly conceived to be in pursuance of the ends exprest in the said Covenant. And the eighth Article, That no Cessation, nor any Pacification or Agreement for Peace whatsoever, shall bee made for either Kingdome, or their Armes, without the mutuall Advice or Consent of both Kingdomes, or their Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees (by vertue whereof wee debated these Propositions with your Lordships) is in pursuance of the same ends. And the ninth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle containeth the publike Faith of the Kingdome of Scotland, That neither our entrance into, nor continuance in the Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land shall bee made use of (wee hope no more by others then by us) to any other ends then are expressed in the Covenant and Articles of this Treaty; And that all matters of Difference shall bee determined by the mutuall Advice and Consent of both Kingdomes, or their Committees: upon the Covenant and Treaty, the Kingdome of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land sending in their Army for your Assistance, emitted to the world a Declaration of their Intentions in that war, shewing their three Motives, three Dueties, and three Ends, conform to the Covenant, and planting it as their <hi>Motto</hi> on all their Banners and Colours, <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Religion, Crown, and Kingdomes,</hi> inserting it in their Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the Lord General, their Directions through the Counties, and Articles of War, and the Military Oath taken by all the Army; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring no otherwise a Blessing upon their Endeavours, then as they shall bee directed to the pursuance of their Ends, inserted in the Title of the Covenant, assuring that the War is not against His Majestie, but that the Wicked being removed, a good understanding may bee established betwixt His Majestie and His People, remembring our publike Faith, given in the ninth of April; And assuring, that their pious, loyall, and faithfull Desires being obtained, wee should most willingly return, esteeming it our greatest Happinesse, that Truth with Peace be established in all His Majesties Dominions.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:179544:22"/>
            <p> As wee a part, so both the Kingdomes together joyned in Arms emitted their joint publike Declaration to the world to the same ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and with many the like Expressions, founding the War on the Covenant, calling it The Cause and Quarrell of God, and ending with a notable Close, <hi>viz.</hi> Wee have after long and grave Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultation resolved and decreed never to lay down Arms, till Truth and Peace by the Blessing of GOD bee settled in this Island upon a firm foundation, for the present and future Generations, which shall bee esteemed of us an abundant reward of all that wee can doe or suffer in this Cause.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:179544:22"/>
               <head>Concerning niformity in Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N August 1642. The Parliament sends down Colonel <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering</hi> to the General Assembly with a Declaration to them, shewing they thought fit to send them a Copie of their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to his Majestie, wherewith he brought also other Declarations, and gave them to the Lords of Secret Councel and Conservers of Peace, that that Church and Kingdom (whereunto they are tied by so many and so neer bonds both Civil and Spirituall) may see that the like minde is now in them, that formerly appeared to be in that Nation, and that they were tender of blood, and zealous for a Reformation of Church and State, which if not interrupted by War, they would settle to the increase of his Majesties honor and State, the Peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity of this Kingdom, and specially to the glory of God, by the advancement of the true Religion, and such a Reformation of the Church, as shall be most agreeable to Gods Word: Out of all which there will also most undoubtedly result, a most firm and stable Union betwixt the two Kingdoms, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Protestation we shall by all good means and wayes upon all occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons labour to preserve and maintain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 792. In their Declaration giving an account to the world of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of their proceedings, they complain that the designe of their Enemies is to alter the constitution and frame of this Government, both in Church and State: And that when they conceived the way to be sufficiently prepared, They at last resolved to put on their Master-piece in Scotland, in imposing upon them a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Service-Book, for well they knew the same fate attended both Kingdoms, and Religion could not be altered in the one without the other. <hi>Ibidem.</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is called the life of their lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 595. The Declaration of the General Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, sent in an answer to a Declaration from the Parliament of England to them, Sheweth, <hi>That the hearts of the godly are grieved, That contrary to their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the Professions both of King and Parliament, the Reformation of Religion moveth so slowly, That it ought first of all to be intended and endeavoured, and that when supreame providence giveth opportunity, no other work can prosper, or successe be durable in the hand of his servants, if it be not apprehended and with all reverence and faithfulnesse improved: And who knoweth but the Lord hath now some controversie with England, which will not be removed, till first and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all, the Worship of his Name and Government of his House, be settled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own will: This niformity they conceive to be most acceptable to God, the surest mean to preserve a solide Peace, without which it can never be expected, and a way to prevent all Heresies and Sects who rent asunder the bowels of Kirk and Kingdom.</hi> And the Lords of Secret Councell joyned with the Assembly in these their desires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 600. <hi>&amp; deinceps.</hi> The Parliament (in their Declaration sent in Answer to a former of ours, thanks the Kirk and Kingdom of Scotland for their desires of Unity in Religion and Uniformity in Church Government in his Majesties three Kingdoms, Sheweth, <hi>That whensoever Religion is subverted or changed in the one, it will easily be accomplished in the other, And desires that we may mutually
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179544:23"/>rejoyce in one anothers happinesse, and yeeld his Majestie such a faithfull subjection as may be honourable to himself, comfortable to his people, and advantagious to the Reformed Churches abroad: Declareth, that they have ever made it their chiefest aime, The Reformation of Church Government and Discipline, and though they finde interruptions and opposition in the prosecution and accomplishment thereof, yet they take our deliverance as a pledge of theirs, hopefull that God will perfit their designes and endeavours of a full Reformation in all matters apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Religion, And acknowledging that this is the greatest honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which God receives from his people, the surest foundation of Glory, strength, and happinesse which he bestows upon any Nation, the best mean to preserve from Sects and Heresies; and to nite these two Nations: Acknowledgeth our serious thoughts and earnest desires for such an nity in Religion, as that in all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Dominions there might be one Confession of Faith, one Directory of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, one publike Catechisme, and one form of Church Government, to be an act of Love to them, and of Wisdom to the good of both Churches, for which they are thankfull to God and us: And although it will hardly be punctually and exactly obtained, unlesse some way be found for a mutuall communication and conjunction of Counsels and Debates, in framing that one Form; Yet both intending the same end, proceeding by the same rule of Gods Word, and guided by the same Spirit, They hope by Gods assistance to be so directed, as to cast out whatsoever is offensive to God, or justly displeasing to any Neighbour Church, and so far to agree with their Brethren of Scotland and other Reformed Churches in all substantiall parts of Doctrine, Worship, and Discipline, as both they and we may enjoy all these ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and conveniences mentioned by us in our last Declaration,</hi> viz. In the more strict Union of both Kingdoms, more safe, easie, and comfortable Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Majestie, and both to himself and people more free communion in all holy Exercises and duties of Worship, more constant security of Religion, against the bloody practises of Papists, and deceitfull Errours of other Sectaries: <hi>They give us hearty thanks for our faithfull and affectionate desires of this so great an advantage for them, And declares that we need not make any Apologie for the same. They further declare, that they are to consult with Godly and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divines, for such a Church-Government as may be most agreeable to Gods holy Word, most apt to procure and conserve the peace of the Church at home, and an happy nion with the Church of Scotland, and other Reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; And for that effect, do desire us to send some Godly and Learned Divines of our Church to that Assembly of theirs, whereby an niformity in Form of Church Government may be obtained, and thereby a more easie passage made to the settling of one Confession of Faith, one Directory of publike Worship, and one Catechisme in all the three Kingdoms, which they hope (through Gods blessing) will have such an effect in all his Majesties Dominions, as will much advance the honour and Service of God, enlarge the greatnesse, power, and glory of the King, confirm the peace, security, and prosperity of all his good Subjects, make way to the relief and deliverance of the poor afflicted Churches abroad, and will tend to the ruine Antichrist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all the Letters and Declarations of the Conservers of the Peace, there is a clear evidence of our earnest pressing Unity in Religion and Peace, with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and tendernesse to his Majesties authority and the Subjects Liberty, And the Parliament of England answers 20 October, That they were willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in all good wayes for the Kings Honour and Happinesse, and Unity and Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between the Kingdoms, Likeas in all their Declarations they expresse their desires for Uniformity in Religion and preservation of his Majesties authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 659. The Parliament in their publike Declaration emitted to the world after the Battell of <hi>Keinton,</hi> sent to Scotland, and given by Colonel <hi>Pickering</hi> in Answer to the Kings Objection, That they countenance Brownists and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179544:23"/>They affirme it to be false and groundlesse: And, that if his Majestie had not denied his consent to the Bill for an Assembly of Divines, they had long since manifested to the world, by a well settled Reformation, their utter dislike of Brownisme and Anabaptisme: But they declare it is one of the Stratagems of the Prelaticall and Malignant partie, to interrupt them in the means to settle Church Government, that by delay thereof they may stir up Factions and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions amongst the people, who having not the Rule before them, are apt to run severall wayes, and so to impute the Errors and indiscreet carriage of a few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons unto the Parliament: But God (they hope) in his good time, will unmask their Plots and confound their devices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 840. The like Objection is made by the King in his Answer to the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners Petition, where it is asked, If the cherishing and countenancing of Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists and Anabaptists, and all manner of Sectaries, be the way to defend and maintain the true Protestant Religion, And <hi>pag.</hi> 845. M. <hi>Pimme</hi> in his Speech to the Citizens of London, in name, and by command of the Parliament answers that Objection amongst others, By denying that the Honourable Houses do give any such countenance to Sectaries, of any kinde whatsoever, and that no such thing can be proved, and retorteth the Argument upon his Majesties keeping of Papists in his Armie. And <hi>pag.</hi> 442. the King gives direction to his Judges to stop the over-hasty growth of Anabaptisme and other Schismes. They declare <hi>pag.</hi> 19. of their Remonstrance, That it is far from their desires and intentions to let loose the reins of Discipline and Church Government, to let private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons or particular Congregations take up what form of Worship they please, but do hold it requisite that there should be throughout the whole Realm, a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to that order which the Law enjoyns, according to the Word of God.</p>
               <p>But above all, let the Declaration directed and sent to the Kingdom of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land 7. Novem. 1642. and delivered to that State by Colonel <hi>Pickering,</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; mentioning, That Scotland had lovingly invited them to a neerer and higher degree of Union in matters concerning Religion and Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which they have most willingly and affectionately embraced, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to pursue, declaring also that a great cause and incentive of the Malice of the Prelaticall and Malignant partie against them, proceeds from the designe they have to hinder the Reformation of the Ecclesiasticall Government in this Kingdom, so much longed for by all the true Lovers of the Protestant Religion: And therefore against such their malice and power, they implore the speedy and powerfull assistance of their Brethren of Scotland, according to the late Act of Pacification, Common dutie of Christianity, and the particular interests of their own Kingdom, which assistance they hope shall produce the preservation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the honour, safety, and peace of his Majestie and all his Subjects, and a more strict conjunction of the Counsels, Designes, and Endeavours of both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for the comfort and relief of the Reformed Churches beyond Sea. All which we did beleeve, and desire to be performed, And did not beleeve the Kings Answer thereunto immediately sent to Scotland against them, as intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to countenance Sects and Schismes, and to subvert his Royall authority.</p>
               <p>In August 1643. The English Commissioners in their first Proposition desire some from our Assembly to be sent to England, to perfit that work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Church Government, and acknowledge that what corruptions take root in England will quickly spread their venome and infection to the Neighbour Church of Scotland, and to ingage us, they presse our interest (although now it is urged by some that we have none) that they were appointed to consult with us concerning such things as might conduce to their Reformation, and their so much desired conjunction with the Church of Scotland.</p>
               <p>The Parliaments Declaration given in by their Commissioners acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth our Christian Zeal and Love in our Endeavours for the necessary Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179544:24"/>of their Church Government and more neer Union of both Churches: And that the two Honourable Houses fully concur with us in these pious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for accomplishment whereof they had called an Assembly and sent down Commissioners, desiring us to give them credit in all things they propose, They call it the cause of God, and shew that we cannot enjoy Religion, Peace, and Liberty, if they be sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>erted in England, the Commissioners invite us to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of a glorious Reformation in England, that God had put in the hearts of both, desires of a neerer Union in Church Government, and for defence against the common Enemies, That God would make use of this opportunity, to knit them both to himself, and each to other in a most strict and durable Union, And thereby the more firmly to establish Truth and Peace in both Nations.</p>
               <p>The same is repeated in their Paper to the Convention of Estates, that the designe of subverting Religion was the same, but <hi>mutata methodo,</hi> That they would secure us from the Invasion of the Irish Rebels, That they needed not Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to invite us to their assistance, Since now the Honourable Houses have so fully declared by what they have done, and what they are desirous to doe, that the true State of the Cause and Quarrell is Religion: In Reformation whereof they are so forward and zealous, as there is nothing expressed in our former or latter Declarations, which they have not seriously taken to heart, and seriously endeavoured to effect, that so the two Kingdoms might be brought to a neerer conjunction in form of Church Government, Directory, Confession, and Catechisme, and utter extirpation of Prelacie. The most effectuall and ready mean whereunto, is now conceived to be the stricter Union and League between the Nations and our assistance of England by an Army.</p>
               <p>And in the Letter from the Assembly of Divines by order of the House of Commons, they call it twice the Cause of Religion, thanketh us for our desires of Uniformity, and imports their laying out a Discipline most agreeable to Gods Word, most apt to preserve the Peace of the Church at home, and neerer agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Church of Scotland, and other Reformed Churches, that so to the utmost of their power, they may exalt him who is the onely Lord, over his Church, his own house, in all his offices, and present the Church as a chaste Virgin unto Christ. They mention the Oath of Assembly concerning Discipline, <hi>viz.</hi> What they conceive most to the glory of God, and good and peace of his Church, and clears the freedom of Assembly to serve their consciences.</p>
               <p>The Assemblies Answer to the Parliament, desires that it may be more and more cleared, Religion to be the true state of the differences in England, and to be uncessantly prosecute first and above all things, <hi>Giving no sleep to their eyes, no slumber to their eye-lids,</hi> untill it be settled; and twice or thrice mentioneth their three Motives, and three ends of Covenant, whereunto they desired the Parliaments concurrence, And so they write to the King, And so in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the Assembly of Divines and Ministers of England, both for Uniformity and the Kings Authority.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="paper">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179544:24"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH PAPER Delivered in to the Houses OF PARLIAMENT BY THE COMMISSIONERS OF SCOTLAND: Containing their Reasons, Why the RESULT of the Committee of both Kingdomes at EDINBURGH 28. Novemb. 1643. is a TREATY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the difference about the Treaty at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 28 <hi>November</hi> 1643. for the better understanding of the whole busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, we shall speak of these heads. First, of the state and condition of affairs before, and at the time of the making of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Secondly, of the powers to make this Treaty. Thirdly, of the Treaty and the conditions thereof. Fourthly, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this Treaty, and the performance thereof. And fifthly, we shall answer the Objections that are alledged why this is not a Treaty.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179544:25"/>
            <p> Concerning the state of affaires before the making of the Treaty, it was this, The Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> according to an agreement made with the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> the 4 of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1642. and the Treaty of the 6 <hi>August.</hi> 1642. sent over an Army into <hi>Vlster</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for suppressing the rebellion in that Kingdome, where they had not long continued, but troubles did arise in this Kingdome, upon the occasion of the difference between the King and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; whereby the supplies promised for entertainment of that Army were withdrawn for the maintenance of the war here, and the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army was driven to so great extremities, that hundreds of them were starved for want of bread, as hath been formerly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to the Houses. About the month of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1643. the enemies power prevailing so farre in <hi>England,</hi> as they were possessed of the most part of the Kingdome, the Houses of Parliament did resolve, and accordingly sent Commissioners into the Kingdome of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to Treat concerning the sending of an Army into <hi>England,</hi> for assistance of their Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> as also to Treat concerning the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> gave them credentiall Letters to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with ample power to negotiate, treat, and conclude, and desired the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to give them full credit in what they should propound. The <hi>English</hi> Commissioners, at first desired the removeall of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, because the Houses of Parliament had found themselves unable to support the charges of that warre: But not long after their arrivall, Generall Major <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> acquaints the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> with the state of affaires in <hi>Ireland,</hi> sends over the Letters directed to him from the Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and Lord Justices of <hi>Ireland,</hi> requiring him to agree to the Cessation, and declareth his inability to resist the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Irish,</hi> joyned together, especially when hee wanted the meanes of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance.</p>
            <p>Further, the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army sends Commissioners into <hi>Scotland</hi> to represent their wants, the necessity of providing a speedy supply of a considerable summe of Money and Victuals, for their present sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, without which they would bee constrained to come away. And these supplies being granted, that as a necessary mean for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of the War, the <hi>English</hi> Army having revolted from the Parliament, the <hi>British</hi> Forces (who except a very few, are all of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Nation) might be joyned with them under one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in chiefe, for opposing the Cessation. Likewise many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of the Inhabitants did petition the Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> for the same purpose, and declared that they would be constrained to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert the Countrey, if the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army were forced to remove: All which being communicated to the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners, they dispatched away to the Houses, and in the meane time wrote to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Major <hi>Monro,</hi> encouraging him to withstand the Cessation, and shewing that they were sent from the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and had power to treat and conclude in such things as concerned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179544:25"/>that Army, and to give good satisfaction to the desires of their Commissioners sent to the Convention of Estates.</p>
            <p>The Houses of Parliament in <hi>September</hi> 1643. being acquainted with the state of Affaires in <hi>Ireland,</hi> findeth necessary to continue the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in their instructions of the first of <hi>November,</hi> appoint their Commissioners to make knowne to their Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> the Votes of both Houses, declaring the Ces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation in <hi>Ireland</hi> destructive to the Protestant Religion, dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>English</hi> Nation, and prejudicial to the interest of the three Kingdomes; and further, appoint them to make knowne that it was the resolution of both Houses to oppose to the utmost the said Ces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, and to encourage, so faras lyes in their power, all those For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Scottish</hi> and <hi>British,</hi> for the utter subduing of those Rebels, and the preventing of setting up Popery in that Kingdome: and in particular for encouragement of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, that they will hasten away with all speed the 60000. l. promised, the 10000. suits of cloathes, and other necessaries. These directions being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and the Agents sent from the Army, being sensible of the great straights and imminent dangers the Army was in, do instantly presse a speedy agreement to their demands, and present advance of a considerable summe of money and quantitie of victualls, without which they will not undertake to stay. And having been disappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for 16. or 17. moneths together of any supply from <hi>England,</hi> they altogether decline to Treat with the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners, but will have the engagement of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is promised them. And upon the other part the <hi>English</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners will not Treat with the Army, but with the Committee of Estates, and earnestly presse their concurrence in giving satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the demands of the Army, and perswading them to stay. These who seriously considered the affaires of <hi>Scotland,</hi> how great an Army they were to send into <hi>England,</hi> and what danger the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, so much weakned of Forces, would be exposed to (whereof since they have sad experience) did incline to the bringing of that Army out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (some Garrisons excepted, according to the first desires of the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners communicated to the States and Army) and so to make up a part of the Armie to be sent into <hi>England,</hi> which would lessen the charge and expence of the Leavy of the Foot by the halfe, and make us stronger at home for suppressing any insurrection, and defending our selves from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion that should happen. Also the Army was more desirous to come into <hi>England</hi> where they had hopes of subsistance, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in <hi>Ireland</hi> where they had experience of very great want. But when it was considered, that if <hi>Scotland</hi> did not presently interpose for the stay of their Army, in all probabilitie, the Kingdome of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would be resigned into the hands of the Rebels, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the well affected in that Kingdome exposed to their cruelty. The Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> being immediatly before joyned in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179544:26"/>for so good ends with their Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> and to drowne their peace in the sea of <hi>Englands</hi> warre, resolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline no hazard or danger whatsoever in prosecution of this cause. And (though then free) did engage themselves for a present sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of money and victualls to enable the stay of that Armie, till the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> should send further supplies for their subsistance.</p>
            <p>Concerning the powers for making of this Treaty, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> had full and ample power to Treat, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and conclude in all things concerning that Army: And that no doubt may remaine here, (if any be) it was the same Committee that did authorize the Covenant and Treaty for <hi>England,</hi> and had a generall power concerning the whole affaires of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>As to the powers of the Commissioners for the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> they had credentiall Letters, signed by the two Speakers in the name of the two Houses of Parliament: Which Letters say, That the Houses had given their Commissioners ample power to negotiate, treat, and conclude; and do desire the Kingdome of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to beleeve whatsoever they should propound. And againe, the Houses in their answer to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> sent by Master <hi>Meldrum,</hi> say, That they have enabled their Commissioners with ample instructions in their names to treat, agree, and conclude all Questions, Doubts, and Demands concerning the arreare and future pay of that Armie, and the continuance or removeall of the same. And (although we are not obliged to enquire after their particular instructions, when their power in generall is so ample) they have by their instructions expresse power for setling the accompts of that Armie; concerning the proportion of the supplies to bee sent to them, and the time of payment is left to their judgement: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the managing of the War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they are expreslie au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized, presently to setle the same to be done by the joynt advice of Committees of both Kingdomes, for preventing the evils and mischiefes that else might fall out, and are onely to make knowne to the Houses what they doe, which is required at the hands of all that are intrusted by any Prince or State, bee their power never so great. And of this power the Commissioners of the Houses did not make the strict use, but agreed upon an alternative, leaving it to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Houses of Parliament which to choose, the stay of the Armie in <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon performance of the Conditions they were appointed to offer; or let the Armie come from thence to bee a part of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army that was to be sent into <hi>England.</hi> And what could the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> do more then this? What was in their owne power to determine as they pleased for the interest and good of their owne affaires, they leave it to the determination of their Brethren to choose either of the two, as they thought most conduceable for the affaires of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Treaty and conditions thereof, the Estates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179544:26"/>of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Commssioners of the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having taken into consideration the dangerous estate of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the demands of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with transported out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or otherwise if they be desired to stay, that they may have a considerable supply of money, and other necessaries presently furnished unto them, assurance given for their future pay, the British joyned with them, and a course setled for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the warre.</p>
            <p>They agree upon 7. Articles, which may be drawne into three heads: First, that the Armie shall stay in <hi>Ireland</hi> till the first of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> and to enable them, there shall be presently advanced by the Committee of Estates and the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners 10000. suits of cloathes, 10000. paire of shooes, 10000. bolls of meale, and 10000. l. in money, and the accompts of the Armie shall bee presentlie made up and concluded. 2. They agree upon an alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native, That betwixt and the first of <hi>February,</hi> 50000. l. shall be really payed and delivered to the Armie, that assurance and security shall be given for their future monthly pay, That he who commands in chiefe over the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie, by joynt advice of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, shall command the rest of the British forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the warre shal be managed by the joynt advice of Committees of both Kingdomes: and in this case the Armie shall be obliged to stay, but in case these conditions shall not be really performed, that then the Armie shall be transported upon the Parliament of <hi>Englands</hi> charge to such parts of <hi>England</hi> as they shall receive orders for from the General of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, and shalbe maintained accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the same establishment as shall be appointed for the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie, and the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to stand still obliged for their whole arrears according to the Treatle of the 6. of <hi>August.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was agreed, that whether they stay in <hi>Ireland</hi> or come from thence, 5000. Armes should be sent unto them.</p>
            <p>The first and last of these are agreed upon without any reservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the second is agreed on by way of alternative, leaving it to the election of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> which they should think fit to choose, yet so as by this Treatie they are positively obliged to the performance of one of the two, wherein the words of the Treaty are very emphatick, when upon a narrative of the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of the Army, it sayes, <hi>It is therefore now agreed, &amp;c.</hi> The conditions are mutuall, the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> perswades the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to stay upon such and such conditions, whom they might have made use of for their owne service; and further, they become sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for <hi>England</hi> that these conditions shall bee performed. The Army thereupon engage themselves, and according to the custome observed in that Kingdome in the like cases, enact them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to stay according to the conditions and termes agreed upon, and a copie of the Act was delivered to the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners upon the other part, as was demanded by the Army, and offered by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179544:27"/>the Houses of Parliament: the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> is interessed in the managing of the warre during the stay of their Army, and such course is setled as may enable them to prosecute the warre accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Covenant. This is all the new obligation on <hi>Englands</hi> part, as for the supply of moneyes and other necessaries in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, the agreement is made much for <hi>Englands</hi> advantage; for whereas they were obliged by a former Treatie for present payment of the whole arreares, the Army is perswaded for the present to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the 5. or 6. part of their arrears, and that not to bee payd till two months after the Treatie. This is the sum of the agreement wherein <hi>Scotland,</hi> formerly bound by no such condition either to <hi>England</hi> or to the Army, now engage themselves to both and for both, upon conditions reciprocally to be performed by the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England;</hi> Here is a <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> and what thing essentiall to a Treatie is deficient, <hi>Obligatio oritur ex contractu, vel quasi, contractus ex consensu reliteris, verbis,</hi> and all these are here, nay, what forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is wanting, for this Treaty is signed by the Clerks of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and ratified by the Parliaments of both respectively: It hath al the names that can be desired, for it is called by the Houses a Result, an Agreement, a Treaty, A transaction between the Kingdoms, and if there were any formality wanting, whereunto we did not look so narrowly, nor stand upon, after such a Covenant, &amp; our engagements to stand and fall with this Kingdome; the lesse Ceremony in such an exigent there was the more confidence, and consequentlie there ought to be the stricter performance, <hi>ubi majorsides ibistrictior ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servantia,</hi> and it is to be considered, that in Treaties between Nations, formalities are different, and as there is no law of Nations concerning formalities and circumstances of Treaties, so there is no agreement or constant practice about them betweene these Kingdomes in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>Before wee speake of the confirmation and performance of this Treatie we shall premise two things. First, that propositions were framed by the Committee of Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> and the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners of both Houses, the 25. <hi>August</hi> 1643. concerning the sending of an Army into <hi>England,</hi> in the preamble of which, it is expresly set down, that these propositions were to be certified with all conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent speed to the two Houses of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the Convention of Estates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to bee respectivelie taken into their considerations, and proceeded with as they shall finde cause, which expressions are not set down in the preamble of these Articles of the 28. <hi>November,</hi> 1643. Onely because there is an alternative in the Treaty, therefore they are to be presented to the Houses who had power to make choise of the stay of the Army, or of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveall at the first of <hi>February,</hi> according to the respective conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mentioned in the Treaty, but are positively obliged to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of one of two, as may appear by these words, <hi>(It is agreed, and it is now agreed)</hi> prefixed to the severall articles, which is not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179544:27"/>done in the propositions of the 25 of <hi>August.</hi> Secondly, that upon the 22. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1642. the Commissioners of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> then residing here, having received a Proposition from the Committee of both Houses for transporting to <hi>Ireland</hi> 2500. men then on foot in <hi>Scotland,</hi> declared they had no instructions so to do till the closure of the Treaty, but were content to offer some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions to the Houses of Parliament, which being granted, they would represent the desires of the Houses to the Councell of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and upon the 24. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> these propositions being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to the Houses, they did agree unto them, and upon the 26. and 27. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> they were approved by his Majestie: these were only Propositions, and propositions to be presented to the Councel of <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet after they were consented unto by the Councell of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it was an obligatory agreement betweene the Kingdomes. We now come to the confirmation of this Treaty, which being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and signed by the Clerks of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of both Kingdomes; The <hi>English</hi> Commissioners upon the 30. of <hi>November,</hi> dispatch away the same to the Houses, with a Letter, wherein they shew the dangerous estate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that in case of the coming away of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, that Kingdome would be resigned up into the hands of the Rebels, that the Parliament had enabled them to promise, but not to performe, or words to that sense: and the Committee of the Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> gave instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to their Commissioners, about that time repairing to <hi>London,</hi> to desire the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to confirme that Treaty, and speedily to performe the conditions therein agreed upon; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the Commissioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> so soone as they come to <hi>London,</hi> and a Committee was appointed by the Houses to Treat with them, gave in a Paper upon the 17. of <hi>February,</hi> to be presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Houses for that purpose; and upon the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> both Houses confirmed the 1, 2, 4, 6, and 7. Articles, whereof that of the managing of the Warre is one, and in ratifying of the 6. Article, the Houses do expresly call it a Treaty. Further, the Houses in answer to the Paper of the Commissioners of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> appoint the Committees of both Houses, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver these Votes of the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> as their consent to the 1, 2, 4, 6, and 7. Articles of the Result of the Committees of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which was done accordingly. Concerning the 3, and 5. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles they returne this answer, That the extremities and wants of this Kingdome were so great, as though they used their endeavours to provide, that 10000. l. present, and 50000. l. in <hi>February,</hi> yet it was not come in, but they hoped within some short time to do it. And because in this case the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army was not obliged to stay, as is agreed upon expresly in the 5. Article: for preventing their coming away, the Houses doe desire the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to co-operate with them so far as lyeth in their power, to keep the said Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the prosecution of the Warre against the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179544:28"/>bloudy Rebels: And do promise, That so far as is possible for the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to doe for the speedy providing of the 60000. l. and setling of a course for their future pay, they will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themselves thereunto with all readinesse and care: in the meane time the 50000. l. not being payed to the Army at <hi>February,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the agreement: The Army gathers together the Ships, and Barks in those parts, presently to transport themselves; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was possible for the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to give any stop, three of the Regiments landed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in a very mutinous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, with intention to Leavy moneys upon the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> for payment of their arreares. And on the other hand there were great grievances amongst the people, by reason of the great taxes and burthens laid upon them, for raising and maintaining the Army sent into <hi>England,</hi> and for reliefe of the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and particularly by reason of the Excise, which being a thing which wanted the practise of former times, and onely for the maintenance of Armies in other Kingdomes, occasioned no small disturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the people, as the Commissioners of the Parliament can bear witnesse. But notwithstanding all these difficulties (whereof we hope the Honourable Houses will never be forgetfull) The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of <hi>Scotland</hi> being verie desirous, so far as was in their power, to co-operate with the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> for the stay of that Armie, forthwith gave power to their Committees (a thing very unusuall in that Kingdome, even in the greatest exigents) to call before them all persons that were able of themselves, or by their credit, to lend or raise moneyes, and to require and ordaine them to lend or give security for such sums of money as they conceived to be proportionable to their estates. And with power to these Committees, in case of refusall, to take such course with them, as in so urgent a necessity they should think fit, to make them advance moneyes, as is before expressed. And by this meanes a considerable proportion of moneyes and provision was forthwith sent to <hi>Ireland</hi> to move them to stay, which they did accordingly. About the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>April,</hi> by the report of Master <hi>Traile,</hi> and Letters from <hi>Scotland,</hi> these things were made knowne to the Houses, and that the Armie had thereupon condescended to stay, notwithstanding they had received no supply from <hi>England</hi> for 20. moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This was also recapitulated in a Paper of the 3. of <hi>April</hi> by the Commissioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who upon these considerations, presse the further resolution of the Houses about the 3. and 5. Articles of the Result of 28. of <hi>November,</hi> shewing that they had no power to do any more or otherwise then was therein agreed: and withall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring the Houses, in case any emergent necessitie of businesse here should interrupt the accomplishment thereof, to declare the resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the 5. Article of the Result, and in a Paper of the 6. of <hi>April,</hi> the Commissioners of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> doe positively desire the Houses to take into consideration the present
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179544:28"/>supply and future subsistance of that Armie, or of transporting and disposing of them otherwise to the good of both Kingdomes, and of giving their last resolution concerning the one or the other, to the Convention of Estates and to the Army, now after foure moneths attendance upon their answer, since the conditions were agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> whereupon the Houses on the 11. of <hi>April,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve and promise, That by the 15. of <hi>May,</hi> 30000. l. should bee provided, and the remainder thereof by the last of <hi>Iune:</hi> and say it is that whereupon the Armie may depend, and for the future main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Scottish and British Forces, that 4000. l. should be payed monthly to the Scottish Army, and the like sum monthly to the British Forces, and the surplusage due to the Scottish Forces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Treaty over and above the said 4000. l. monthly, to be secured to them upon the publick Faith. Concerning the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief; they declare that the Earle of <hi>Leven</hi> is Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in chief of the British, as well as <hi>Scots,</hi> according to the 4. Article of the Result of the Committees of both Kingdomes, passed both Houses, which they mention in these Votes, as the ground obliging them in that particular, and desire his Excellence to appoint a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief in his absence: and for the managing of the war, they resolve that Committees be nominated, and appointed by the joynt advice of both Kingdomes to reside on the place for regulation of these Forces, and better carrying on of that Warre.</p>
            <p>Further, upon the 25. of <hi>May,</hi> the honourable Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wrote a letter to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> acquainted them that they had ratified and confirmed the severall Treaties made and agreed between their Commissioners and the Estates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and it is their desire the same may be done by the Parliament of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Also they professe themselves, verie sensible of the great wants and extremities which the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie in <hi>Ireland</hi> hath borne with much patience, occasioned by the manifold distractions and great necessities of this Kingdome, and doe returne their heartie thanks to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for their care of that Army, and the great charge they have been at for their relief, with provisions and money for their necessarie subsistance: They likewise in that letter make knowen what they have done in pursuance of their resolutions of the 11. of <hi>April,</hi> and promise performance of the rest according to the said resolutions, by all which it is most cleare and evident, that the Houses did choose the first part of the alternative concerning the stay of the Army, whereas if they had seasonablie chosen the last part concerning their transport, the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> had been free of a great burthen of entertaining that Armie in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and needed not to have beene at the charge of raising so many foot to bring into <hi>England.</hi> We come now to answer the objections, which as at the debate we desired to know, if we repeated them faithfully, so if there be any mistake now we shall upon information be readie to rectifie the same.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179544:29"/>
            <p> It is objected from the preamble of this Treatie, that these were only propositions to be presented to the Houses, and so onely prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory for their resolution, without any obligation of a Treatie.</p>
            <p>To which we answer. That the reason of this was because the Treatie consisted of an alternative, and it was left to the Houses to choose the one part of the alternative or the other, with the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein expressed, but in all other things the Treatie was then fully agreed upon, as may appear by comparing them with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of the 25. of <hi>August,</hi> in the preamble of which it is clearly expressed, that the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> or convention of Estates, may alter or change them as they shall finde cause: but there is no such expression in the preamble of these, onely it is said they were agreed upon to be presented to the Houses, and these not as naked propositions, but as particulars already agreed to by their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, as is prefixed to the Articles, to the end they migh thee confirmed: Only this was left free, that the Houses might make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of one part of the Alternative, and that it is not also to bee presented to the convention of Estates or Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is as cleare, for that the Committee of Estates did not reserve a power to determine concerning the stay or removeall of the Army, but left the same to the Houses of Parliament, upon the conditions expressed in the agreement, and therefore did finally conclude for their part upon the whole, the exigent beeing such as would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a delay, till the meeting of the Parliament in <hi>May</hi> following, because things were presently to be performed in matter of supply and accompts, to perswade the stay of the Army till the first of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary:</hi> And there was also a necessitie of giving satisfaction to the Army presentlie, what should be their conditions, if they should be desired to stay after the first of <hi>February,</hi> and what should bee their conditions if they came away, which were then agreed upon by both Kingdomes: Onely concerning the alternative there was no deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination for the present on <hi>Englands</hi> part, it being at the desire of the Commissioners left to the election of the Houses. And whereas it was affirmed that these Articles were not obligatory, we leave it to the Houses and all understanding men to judge, whether this could have given any satisfaction to the Army to stay, or the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to engage, if it had been then said unto them by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> We wil make an agreement with you, but it must not be obligatory but alterable at the pleasure of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> But for a further answer, consider the propositions of the 24. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1642. these were onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, and propositions to be presented to the Councell of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> alone, the Houses having alreadie agreed, and the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Scotland</hi> having declared they had no power in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet we believe there is none will say that after the Councell of <hi>Scotland</hi> had also agreed to these propositions, notwithstanding their consent, they were not obliged to send the 2500 men into <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:179544:29"/>or when <hi>Scotland</hi> had performed their part, that the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> was not obliged to performe the conditions agreed unto on their part, but might alter them at their pleasure; And how much more ought this agreement to be observed where nothing essentiall to a Treatie, nor any necessarie formalitie is wanting, seeing also the propositions of the 25. of <hi>August,</hi> that were unquestionably al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable by the Houses, are after confirmation esteemed a Treaty ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory, and not alterable at pleasure of one of the parties, which we conceave to be essentiall to all Treaties made between Nations, or contracts between persons, &amp;c. they being <hi>primo libertatis sed postea necessitatis,</hi> free before consent, but not after, neither can it make any materiall difference, that the propositions of the 25. of <hi>August,</hi> were afterward signed by the Commissioners of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the authority being all one whether they be subscribed by Commissioners or Clerks of the Parliament of both Kingdomes: for the agreement the 24. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1642. and the Treaty concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the sending the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army into <hi>Ireland</hi> 6. <hi>August</hi> 1642. are only signed by the Clerks of the two Parliaments respectively.</p>
            <p>But sayes the opponent, It is acknowledged to bee a Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdomes, and to bee an agreement between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, but not a Treaty with such and such formalities, it is a Treaty in one sense, but not in such a sense as the other Treaties; they are obligatory, and this is not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This seems to us very strange Doctrine, since there is no law of Nations nor constant practise or custome between these Kingdoms, concerning the formalities of a Treaty, we never understood such a distinction of Treaties and agreement between Kingdoms before, as some obligatory and some not; and to tell us now, and never till now, two yeares and a halfe after the agreement, and after <hi>Scotland</hi> hath performed their part of it, that this is not a Treaty in that sense that other Treaties are; Whatsoever be the mindes of private persons, we trust it will be very farre from the Honourable Houses of Parliament to approve of such a distinction: And how ever it may relish with some now, it would have been very evil Rhethorick, the 28. of <hi>November</hi> 1643. to perswade the <hi>Scots</hi> Army to stay in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to engage for their intertainment, to say in plain <hi>English,</hi> there are diverse senses and diverse natures of Treaties, some that are not, and some that are alterable at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, of one of the parties, and that after their owne confirmation and performance made by the other partie. 2. Another objection was, that they are of the nature of Ordinances, and containe nothing which may imply the construction of a Treaty.</p>
            <p>To which we answer. 1. That the votes of the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> were delivered unto us by the appointment of both houses as their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the Articles of the Result and Treaty of the Committee of both Kingdomes 28. of <hi>November</hi> 1643. and the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is thereupon desired by the Houses to co-operate with them so
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179544:30"/>farre as was in their power, for stay of that Army in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 2. These Articles are ratified as things past of the same date. 3. The Committee of the Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> are therein made undertakers and advancers of moneys and provisions, who can no way come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of an ordinance of the Houses of Parliament. 4. The votes of the 11. of <hi>April,</hi> do mention the Result of the 28. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> passed both Houses as the foundation and obligation upon which they are grounded, and suppose it were an Ordinance, it bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made to satisfie another Nation engaged in an agreement at their desire, and to answer the demands of an Army of strangers, whom they had taken on in their service, and for 20. monthes together left destitute of all manner of supply, we hope the Houses will not judge such an Ordinance alterable at pleasure. 5. We have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmation of the propositions of the 24. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> nor of the Treatie of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> but the votes of the Houses in the same manner.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It was objected that in the propositions of peace formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on, all the Treaties are enumerated together and desired to be confirmed, and this Treaty is not there enumerated, but is named as an Ordinance.</p>
            <p>We answer. That at the framing of the propositions it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived inconvenient to present that whole Treaty to the King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it would lay open too much to our enemies the wants and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses of that Army, and in particular, it was conceived, not neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to desire ratification of that part which looked to the time past, but onely what related to the future, which was mainly the Article concerning the Command in chiefe, and managing of the war. And it being agreed upon in the 17. proposition that the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia of the Kingdomes should be setled in Commissioners of both Kingdomes, and that as a joynt Committee, they should have power to order the warre of <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the ordinance of the 11. of <hi>April,</hi> (which is founded upon the result of the 28. of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> as is therein expressed) And further, to order the Militia, and conserve the peace of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> this was judged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to the enumeration of it, amongst the other Treaties, and carryed this further advantage with it, That it did avoyd the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences afore mentioned. This was the true reason of the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it in that place, and provided that the 17. proposition may stand as formerly, we shall not desire this Treaty to be expressed any other wayes, or in any other place: and why any mistake of expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in us, who did not then make such a difference (as now we have cause to doe) betwixt a Treaty and an Ordinance, or votes reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the substance thereof, and in the body of it mentioning the Treaty as the obligation on which it was founded, should be urged as an argument to prove this no Treaty, we cannot understand, sith the Houses of Parliament do alledge that they are not only not obliged to expressions made in these propositions, but also may, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179544:30"/>also have changed the most materiall things in these Propositions. Certainly if one of the Kingdomes be not obliged to the matter or forme of these Propositions, the other is not. But that it may suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appear to the Honourable Houses, that wee have no other thoughts now then we had then, and so farre as we know, was then also the minde of the Houses themselves: We desire that our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the 28. of <hi>October,</hi> 1644. may be perused, which was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into the Houses immediatly upon the concluding of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, and before they were sent to <hi>Oxford,</hi> wherein wee desire, that according to the 6. Article of the Treaty at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 28. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 1643. confirmed by the Houses in their Votes of the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> there be sent over to <hi>Carickfergus</hi> 5000. Armes, for the use of the Scottish Armie, and an answer thereunto, the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons do call it, The Treaty at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the 28. <hi>November,</hi> since confirmed by the Houses in their Votes of the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that reference the Committee of both Houses having conferred with us, and reported their opinions, both Houses gave order for furnishing of those Armies accordingly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Objection was, That the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> did call from <hi>Ireland</hi> some of that Army for their own assistance.</p>
            <p>To this wee answer. 1. That when the Houses of Parliament desired the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> to send an Army into <hi>England</hi> for their assistance, their Commissioners gave in a Paper to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Estates in these words, <hi>[And for the better encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland <hi>to this necessary and so much desired Vnion, we are by both Houses of Parliament authorized to assure their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, That if they shall be annoyed or indangered by any Force or Armie, either from</hi> England, <hi>or from any other place, the Lords and Commons in</hi> England <hi>will assist them with a proportionable strength of Horse and Foot, to what their Brethren shall now afford them to bee sent into</hi> Scotland <hi>for the defence of that Kingdome, and they will maintaine a guard of Ships at their owne charge upon the coasts of</hi> Scotland, <hi>for the securing of that Kingdome from the invasion of the</hi> Irish <hi>Rebels, or other enemies, during such time as the Scottish Armie shall be imployed in the defence of the Kingdome of</hi> England.] And though this was particularly agreed upon by Treaty, yet it is well known to the Houses of Parliament that this was not performed, which considered, wee trust they will have a good construction of the calling away a small number from that Army, for their owne necessary defence against a farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of <hi>Irish</hi> Rebels.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is provided by the large Treaty between the Kingdomes, that in case any Armies be levyed or neighbours wronged, as the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> was in a great measure, by those barbarous <hi>Irish</hi> subjects of the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> The Estates of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by which it was done, are obliged to pursue, take, and punish the offenders with all rigour. And incase any of the subjects of any of the Kingdomes shall rise in Armes, or make Warre against the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179544:31"/>Kingdome or subjects thereof, without consent of the Parliament of that Kingdome whereof they are subjects, or upon which they do depend (which is expressed, because of <hi>Irelands</hi> dependance on <hi>England,</hi> under the which, it is agreed in that Treatie to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in all the Articles thereof) that they shall be held and demaind as Traitors to the Estate whereof they are subjects; and that State or Kingdome is bound, and gives their publick Faith to concurre with the other to represse them, and if <hi>England</hi> was bound to send Forces forsuppressing these Rebells, we might with far greater reason recall some of our owne Forces to oppose those very enemies whom they were sent into <hi>Ireland</hi> to pursue.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They were uselesse in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by reason supplies were not sent them according to the Treaty, to enable them for service there, and were better employed in delivering <hi>Scotland</hi> from those who had invaded that Kingdome, for no other quarrell but for the assistance sent unto <hi>England,</hi> and in preventing an invasion of <hi>England,</hi> which the late Earle of <hi>Montrose</hi> and the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebels professed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be their maine intention and designe.</p>
            <p>A 5. Objection was, That the Committee of both Houses were appointed to Treat with the <hi>Scottish</hi> Commissioners here, about the ascertaining the intertainment of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army in <hi>England;</hi> this was a Treaty, but what was done by the Committee of both Houses was not obligatory. We answer. That the Committee of both Houses had no power to Treat, agree and conclude, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Treat and report; yea, they were expresly limited not to make a Result, but appointed to report their opinions, with the reasons of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Commissioners apart: and where there is no power to make a Result, certainly there can be no Treaty; also the case is wholly different, as may be made easily appeare, but because this argument was not insisted upon, wee shall insist on the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of it.</p>
            <p>A 6. Objection was, That the Houses did delay the Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the 3. and 5. Articles, and when they gave their resolution upon them, they varied the dayes for payment of the moneys, and did not ratifie the 5. Article, as it was presented.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot see where the strength of this argument lyeth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it be to commend the readinesse of the Kingdome of <hi>Sctoland,</hi> who in the interim furnished moneys and provisions to that Armie, and the patience of the Army, who notwithstanding all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer sufferings, did wait for these supplies so long after the time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon in the Treaty. Concerning the not ratifying of the 5. Article, as it was presented, we are forced again to remember that which seemes to be forgotten all along the debate, That there is an Alternative in the 5. Article, and the Houses could not ratifie both parts of the Alternative, which are directly opposite, whereof the one doth concerne their stay, the other their removall.</p>
            <p>A 7. Objection was, That there was no stipulation on <hi>Scotlands</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179544:31"/>part, for by the Treatie the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to stay in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and if the conditions be not mutuall, and sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulatory, the whole foundation of this Treatie is taken away.</p>
            <p>For answer. We desire it may be considered, that the Army, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Treaty, was to be monthly payed, and they were not obliged to stay till they were starved, though such were the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of many of them. But which removes it beyond all excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or scruple the Armie had then, for about 16. moneths received no supplies from <hi>England,</hi> (which wee beleeve no age can paralell) and the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> according to their instructions in <hi>Iuly</hi> 1643. had declared, their owne troubles did so increase, that they were not able to maintaine them, and therefore desired the Estates of <hi>Scotland</hi> to withdraw them from <hi>Ireland,</hi> except a few to bee left for Garrisons, and offered all meanes in the power of the Houses for satisfying their Arrears, according to the Treaty the 6. <hi>August.</hi> Now being thus dis-ingaged by the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust,</hi> and the Army thereupon willing to come away, they were not obliged to stay, when afterwards upon no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap>ice of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of the Parliaments Forces, and making a Cessation with the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebels, their stay was found necessary, and desired by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> Neither was the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> at all obliged to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine that Army, nor to send them supplies, as they did engage themselves to do by this second Treaty, at the desire of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was lastly objected, That these Articles were of a diverse na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, six of them are obligatorie, as being grounded upon the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> but that concerning the managing of the war is of another nature, having no <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> neither was it the cause of the stay of the Army, and therefore not obligatorie, and though the whole Articles were obligatory, yet the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> failing in performance to <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> was free to break on the other side, and there is an end of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>This of all other appeares to be most strange, for it makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a Treaty and Common discourse, if one Kingdome break to another, suppose it were in the least cirumstance, the other Kingdome is by this tenet set at liberty to breake in the whole, and so the Treaty to be for ever dissolved, as if it had never been. To this we shall answer no further, but that this argument makes a Treaty (which is a thing most sacred and inviolable to be keept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Kingdomes) to be of such a nature as either Kingdome may dissolve it at pleasure, without any reparation to be had, or account to be sought by the other, and consequently there is not, nor cannot be any obligatory Treaty between the Kingdomes. To the first part of the Argument, that six of the Articles are obligatory and one is not. We answer, that by the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> was obliged to pay the whole arreares of the Army, extending then to above three hundreth thousand pounds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179544:32"/>sterling, as may appeare by the accompts signed, and concluded by the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners immediatly after this Treaty, 28. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1643. And in this new Treaty the Army was content for that present to accept of the 5. or 6. part of their arreares, and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they had been so often disappointed of what was promised them, they demanded this further security, That the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> might be surety for <hi>Englands</hi> performance, which they had not in the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> some of these Articles are not at all mentioned in the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> as the 6. and 7. Articles, and the rest, though they may have the same mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with some Articles of the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> yet are they agreed upon in a different manner: And that it may appear that the 4. Article of this Treaty concerning the Command in chiefe, and managing of the Warre, is not altogether now, as this Objection seemes to hold forth, we desire it may be remembred, that in the 3. Article of the Propositions of the 24. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1642. it is agreed, That if it shall be thought fit that any Regiments or Troupes of <hi>Vlster</hi> shall joyne with the <hi>Scots</hi> Forces, that they shall receive Orders from the Commander of the <hi>Scottish</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in the 9. Article of the Treaty of the 6. of <hi>August,</hi> it is agreed that the inhabitants of all Townes and villages in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie shall be, the Country people shall rise and concurre with them, when the Commanders of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army shall thinke fit for the service, and shall receive Orders and directions from them, and in the 10. Article of that Treaty, if the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie shall joyne with any other Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> The Generall of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie, shall onely Cede to the Kings Lieutenant, his deputy, or any other who shall have the chiefe government of that Kingdome, derived from the Crowne of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and otherwise, the Generall of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, and have the Command of all others: and when this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was made, there was no other meane left for preserving that Kingdome from utter ruine, but to joyne with the <hi>Scottish</hi> and <hi>British</hi> Forces under one Command for opposing the Cessation. And it is to be considered, that whereas by the which Article of the Treaty 6. of <hi>August,</hi> the prosecution of the Warre of <hi>Ireland</hi> by the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie, is left to the judgement of the Commanders of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, as they shall think most expedient for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King, and Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and only in the case of conjunction with the Kings Lieutenant, or Deputy by authority from the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> they are to receive instructions from them in an honourable way, to whom he is onely to Cede, and to precede all others. By this new Treaty, the Commanders of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army, subject themselves to the orders and directions of a Committe of both Kingdomes, whereby their power is so farre diminished and limited which it was not before. Also, this is onely to continue during the warre, and is at an end, how soone
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179544:32"/>a peace is setled, or that the <hi>Scottish</hi> Armie shall be satisfied and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed, whereof we shall be heartily content. Whereas it is said, there is not a <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> that hath beene answered formerly, the stay of an Army after it hath been starved 16. monthes to save a Kingdome, is a <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> their sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding supplyes to that Army, is a <hi>quid pro quo,</hi> and for that which is said, that in the 5. Article it is expressed, that in case the 50000. l. be not payd in <hi>February,</hi> the Army would not stay. And therefore, the condition of the money was the cause of their stay, and not the condition for the managing of the warre: It is no consequence, for it was expresly demanded by the Armie, and they would not stay so much, as to the first of <hi>February,</hi> without the conjunction of the <hi>British</hi> Forces, in manner aforesaid, because of the strength of the enemie, and therefore it was expreslie agreed upon in the 4. Article, and that their stay is mainlie pitched upon the payment of the money, the reason is cleare, because the meane of their subsistance is the Primarie condition, and necessarily presupposed, as the cause <hi>sine quo non,</hi> to which the conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Forces and managing of the warre is but secondary, and without it altogether unprofitable. And to conclude the whole debate, we desire it may be observed, that whereas by the Votes of the Houses it was appointed, that the Committee of both Houses should make it appeare to us, that the transactions at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 28. <hi>November,</hi> 1643. was no Treaty: It was acknowledged in the debates on Saturday, the 28. of <hi>March</hi> last, that these transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were an agreement between the Kingdomes, and a Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdomes, but not a Treatie in such a sense as other Treaties that are obligatorie: and in the debates on Monday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, it was acknowledged to be obligatory in some, but not in all the Articles thereof. To which we make this answer. That the Commissioners of the Houses of Parliament, had a generall power to Treat, agree, and conclude, and in their Credentiall Letters given by the Houses to their Commissioners, there is no such distinction. 2. When the <hi>English</hi> Commissioners agree with the Estates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they make no such distinction, nor is there any such distinction of diverse natures or senses in the Articles, as they are set down and agreed on, nor can they admit of any other interpretation then is expressed in the Articles themselves. 3. There is no such distinction made, when these Articles are ratified and confirmed by the Houses: Had any such distinction beene made known before the agreement, the time of the agreement, or the time of the confirmation (which without the clear expression of it, could never be apprehended by the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi>) there had been some colour for such an objection: but the Articles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing agreed on by Commissioners, having full and ample power, the agreement being granted upon demands of an Armie, left at
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179544:33"/>liberty to come away, and upon the offers and promises of the Houses, there being mutuall conditions between the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and conditions being performed on <hi>Scotlands</hi> part, being ratified by the Houses, called by them, an Agreement, A Treatie, an Assurance, that upon which the Army might depend, and the Votes of the Houses delivered to us, as their consent to this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> being thereupon desired by the Houses to co-operate for the stay of the Army, and a Letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written from the Houses to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them that they had ratified the severall Treaties between the Kingdomes, we having still demanded the performance of it, as a Treaty confirmed by the Houses, and no exception made, but still acknowledged as a Treaty till now. Upon these considerations wee are confident the honourable Houses will never deny it to bee a Treaty, wherein we are the more confirmed, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of both Houses, having taken a day to answere our argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and after that another, made no reply, wee having also at the close of the debate offered to their Lordships; That if they had any further scruples or doubts, we were ready and confident to give them satisfaction, and withall desired, that if any other papers were made use of, concerning this businesse then we had seen, they might be Communicated unto us, that nothing might be wanting which might give the honourable Houses full satisfaction.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179544:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>